卢旺达饭店
由于停火过晚 没能挽救这些村庄…
The latest ceasefire came too late to save these villages...
今天克林顿总统表示将密切关注
Today President Clinton voiced concerns
萨拉热窝日益恶化的局势…
at the deteriorating situation in Sarajevo...
当人们问我 尊敬的听众朋友们
When people ask me, good listeners,
为什么我讨厌所有的图西族人
why do I hate all the Tutsi,
我说 “去看看我们的历史吧”
I say, "Read our history. "
图西族曾通敌比利时殖民者
The Tutsi were collaborators for the Belgian colonists.
他们强占我们胡图族的土地 用鞭子抽我们
They stole our Hutu land, they whipped us.
现在这些图西族反叛分子 他们回来了
Now they have come back, these Tutsi rebels.
他们如同蟑螂 他们是杀人犯
They are cockroaches. They are murderers.
卢旺达是我们胡图族的领地 我们才是主人
Rwanda is our Hutu land. We are the majority.
他们则是少数叛国者和侵略者
They are a minority of traitors and invaders.
我们要粉碎他们的横行 消灭RPF反叛分子
We will squash the infestation. We will wipe out the RPF rebels.
你收听的是RTLM（千丘广播电台）胡图族官方电台
This is RTLM, Hutu Power Radio.
保持警惕 防范邻居
Stay alert. Watch your neighbors.
-=TLF字幕组=-
翻译：KOK
校对：KOK
基加利（卢旺达首都） 1994
- 卢斯赛伯吉纳先生 谢谢 - 见到你很高兴 先生
- Mr, Rusesabagina, thank you, - Good to see you, sir,
谢谢
Thank you,
这些事给你的 先生 刚从哈瓦那（古巴首都）带来的
These are for you, sir, They're fresh from Havana,
太棒了 下次你去那儿代我向菲德尔问好
Wonderful, Next time you are there, tell Fidel that I said hello,
先生们 很高兴见到你们
Good to see you gentlemen,
片名：卢旺达饭店
那是支上等的雪茄 先生
That is a fine cigar, sir,
这是Cohiba牌的雪茄（注：Cohiba是世界顶级雪茄烟品牌）
This is a Cohiba cigar,
- 每一支值10,000法郎 - 10,000法郎？
- Each one is worth 10,000 francs, - 10,000 francs?
是的 不错 但对我来说比10,000法郎还值钱
Yes, yes, But it is worth more to me than 10,000 francs,
怎么讲 先生？
What do you mean, sir?
要是给一个商人10,000法郎 这对他来说意味着什么？
If I give a businessman 10,000 francs, what does that matter to him?
他不缺钱的 但是…如果我给他一支Cohiba牌的雪茄
He is rich, But if I give him a Cohiba cigar
直接从古巴首都哈瓦那带回来的…嘿 这就体面了 杜比
straight from Havana, Cuba,,, Hey, that is style, Dube,
是蛮体面
Style,
Cohiba――不可思议的雪茄
Cohiba--a fantastic cigar,
是最好的 对吧？
The best, eh?
那今天的集会 你会来参加吧？
So, you're going to join us at the rally today?
我会尽力而为 乔治
I will try my best, George,
这些日子我没时间参加集会和政治活动
but these days I have no time for rallies and politics,
政治就是权势 保罗 胡图族的权势
Politics is power, Paul, Hutu power,
以及财富
And money,
现在是你加入的时候了
It's time for you to join your people,
谢谢 乔治
Thank you, George,
但是时间也是金钱
But time is also money,
今天我要在常规订单的基础上
I need six extra cases of beer today,
再加六箱啤酒
along with the regular order,
- 饭店生意很好嘛 - 非常好
- Business is good at the hotel, - It is very good,
见到你总是很高兴 保罗
I'm always glad to see you, Paul,
放回去！放回去！那不是啤酒！
Put that back! Put that back! That's not beer!
- 你 来收拾一下 - 好的 先生 来
- You, clean this up, - Yes, sir, Come on,
保罗 嘉士伯牌的没了 但别担心
Paul, don't worry about the Carlsberg,
我会给你喜力牌的 我不向你额外收费
I'll give you Heineken, and I won't charge you extra,
谢谢
Thank you,
从中国买的便宜货――每把十分钱
A bargain buy from China-- ten cents each,
知道吗 我至少能卖五十分
You know, I'll get at least fifty,
至少
At least,
乔治・卢塔甘达是个坏人
George Rutaganda is a bad man,
我在广播上听到 他叫胡图族屠杀所有图西族人
I've heard him on the radio telling the Hutus to kill all the Tutsis,
卢塔甘达那帮人 都是白痴 杜比
Rutaganda and his people, they are fools, Dube,
他们的好景到头了
Their time is soon over,
不管怎样 这是谈生意
Anyway, this is business,
- 噢 不 是部族民兵 - 按他们说的做 靠边
- Oh, no, It's the lnterhamwe, - Do as they say, Pull over,
别 别 坐直 杜比 坐直
No, no, sit up, Dube, Sit up,
带点笑容 杜比 别引人注目
Smile, Dube, Don't attract attention to yourself,
这些人有的是我邻居 他们知道我是图西族人
Some of these men are my neighbors, They know that I'm Tutsi,
稍微笑笑 就好像大家都是朋友 杜比
Just smile as if they are friends, Dube,
- 我认识这个人！ - 你是图西族人？
- I know this man! - Are you a Tutsi?
你在这儿干什么？
What are you doing here?
不 不 胡图族势力 胡图族势力 胡图族势力！
No, no, Hutu power, Hutu power, Hutu power!
好 是的！
Okay, Yes!
离开这儿
Get out of here,
箱子里有水渗出
There's water coming from the box,
停在这儿 我们从前面走
Park here, We'll go in the front,
格莱戈瓦 请帮忙把水拖一下
Gregoire, please help with this water,
格莱戈瓦！
Gregoire!
马上来拖
Deal with this right away,
我们希望看到歹徒
We were hoping to go see the gorilla.
你应该和我们旅行队联系一下
You must contact our safari desk,
杜比 这儿是大厅
Dube, this is the lobby,
- 怎么回事？ - 抱歉 先生 紧急情况
- What's going on? - I am sorry, sir, It is an emergency,
- 噢 见鬼！ - 噢 抱歉 先生
Oh, shit! Oh, sorry, sir,
十只活的 十二只死的
Ten alive, twelve are dead,
不要紧
All right,
把壳留着
But save the shells,
用东西…
Fill them with,,,
…填满 用精肉和当地的一些食物
,,,a stuffing, The good meat and something local,
- 木薯行吗？ - 还有…鱼肉
- Cassava? - And,,,the fish,
- 还有面包皮 - 是的
- And tipali, - Yes,
就叫作“木薯面包鲜龙虾”
We'll call it "fresh lobster in a cassava and tipali crust,"
杜比
Dube,
够体面 先生
Style, sir,
是的 先生
Yes, sir,
比齐蒙戈将军 问题在于 我得知
The problem is, General Bizimungu, I have information
部族民兵不会接受和平协定
that the lnterhamwe militia will not heed the peace agreement,
上校 联合国 不必担心部族的问题
Colonel, the U,N, need not worry about the lnterhamwe,
我们能有效控制他们
We will control them,
- 将军 - 保罗
- General, - Paul,
这瓶苏格兰威士忌不同寻常
This scotch is exceptional,
这是我们最受欢迎的单一麦芽威士忌 我知道你会喜欢的
It is our most popular single malt, I knew you'd like it,
奥利弗上校 很荣幸见到您 先生
Colonel Oliver, it is a pleasure to see you, sir,
见到你很高兴 保罗
Good to see you, Paul,
将军 我来介绍一下今天的龙虾
General, let me recommend the lobster for lunch today,
是精心准备的――空运来的
It is spectacular-- straight off the plane,
基加利鲜龙虾 你让我们感到自豪 保罗
Fresh lobster in Kigali, You do us proud, Paul,
谢谢
Thank you,
在存衣处 我也给你留了点
I left a little something for you at the coat check,
抱歉 先生们
Excuse me, gentlemen,
还需要面粉 给我两袋面粉
I need flour, Give me two bags of flour,
好了 开饭了 来啦
Okay, the plates are ready, Here they come,
下午好 女士们
Good afternoon, ladies,
伊丽莎白 拜托把这个放到将军的衣箱里
Elizabeth, please put these in the general's briefcase,
好的 先生
Yes, sir,
这是RTLM（千丘广播电台） 胡图族官方电台
This is RTLM, Hutu Power Radio.
我要带给总统先生一个消息
I have a message for our president.
警惕 别相信图西族反叛分子
Beware. Do not trust the Tutsi rebels.
别和他们握手 他们会杀了你
Do not shake the hand that will stab you.
他们对待你会像…
They will treat you...
…来自卢旺达首都基加利的报道 这里气氛高度紧张
... reporting from Kigali, Rwanda, where tensions are high
由于签署联合国和平条约的最后期限正在逼近
as the deadline for the U. N.-brokered peace agreement approaches.
你好啊 保罗先生
Hello, Mr, Paul,
你好 耶利米
Hello, Jeremiah,
你好 先生
Hello, sir,
- 很高兴见到你 保罗 - 奥德特
- Good to see you, Paul, - Odette,
回头见
See you soon,
你弟弟和女孩们都在这儿
So your brother and the girls are here,
是的
Yes,
一、二、三…
One, two, three,,,
噢 卡琳！
Oh, Carine!
好 爱耐丝 我看看 轮到你了
Okay, Anais, let me see, Your turn,
一、二、三…
One, two, three,,,
- 谁赢了？ - 噢 这不重要
Who is the winner? Oh, it doesn't matter,
我带了巧克力 谁要巧克力？
I have chocolates, Who wants chocolates?
嗨 爸爸 看这个
Hey, Papa, watch this,
噢 天哪 呃 这儿 巧克力 巧克力 谁想要？
Oh, my goodness, Well, here, chocolates, chocolates, Who wants?
给保罗叔叔说谢谢
Say thank you to your Uncle Paul,
- 拜托 别在饭前吃 - 别在饭前吃哦 你妈妈说了
- Please, not before dinner, - Not before dinner, Mama says,
- 谢谢 - 好的 好的
- Thank you, - Okay, okay,
我们进去
Let's go in,
商店的生意不景气 饭店情况怎么样？
Things are very slow at the shop, How are things at the hotel?
很忙 很多人来看暴徒
Very busy, Many people visiting the gorillas,
很多外国记者为和平协定而来…
A lot of foreign press arriving for the peace acc--
- 怎么了？ - 有士兵
- What? - There are soldiers,
- 哪儿？ - 就在路上
- Where? - On the street,
我去看看怎么回事 没事儿
I'll go see what's happening, It's all right,
- 我们知道你是图西族的 - 求求你了 先生 他是我丈夫
- We know you are Tutsi, - Please, sir, this is my husband,
- 他只是个园丁 - 他替反叛分子当间谍
- He's just a gardener, - He's been spying for the rebels,
- 不 我们不认识反叛分子 - 你跟我们走！
- No, we do not know any rebels, - You will come with us!
不 我们说的都是实话 我们不认识…
No, we are telling the truth, We do not know any,,,
- 怎么了？ - 别出声！
- What is it? - Shut up!
塔莎娜 回屋里去 你快回去
Tatiana, go back in the house, You must go back,
- 你别出来 - 是维克托
- You mustn't be out here, - It's Victor,
别 上校 你看…
No, Captain, you see--
不是我 不是我 上校 上校
It's not me, It's not me, Captain, Captain,
为什么带他走？求求你了 求求你了
Why are you taking him away? Please, please,
- 我知道 我知道 但不是我干的 - 你们这帮图西族白痴
- I know, I know, but it's not me, - You Tutsi fuckers,
不！不！
No! No!
我们得想想办法
We must do something,
- 想什么办法？ - 叫人
- Do what? - Call someone,
我不去 我不去
I'm not going, I'm not going,
别！
No!
带到车上去 马上！
Get him in the truck, Now!
我们得想想办法
We must do something,
求求你帮帮他！
Please help him!
噢 维克托！
Oh, Victor!
维克托！
Victor!
我们无能为力
There is nothing we can do,
- 你今晚不能走 托马斯 - 好的
- You must stay the night, Thomas, - Yes,
不！
No!
他们为什么抓维克托？
Why would they arrest Victor?
他没从事过政治活动啊
He has no politics,
- 他是园丁 - 谁知道 塔莎？
- He's a gardener, - Who knows, Tatsi?
谁知道？
Who knows?
有人看不惯他 就说他替反叛分子当间谍
Someone who didn't like him denounced him as a rebel spy,
一直有这种事发生
Happens all the time now,
或许你可以联系一下军队里的熟人
Maybe you could call one of your contacts in the army,
没用的
It wouldn't help,
你可以让他帮帮忙
You could ask as a favor,
不 我不
No, I could not,
塔莎 我整天都在取悦于这个军官、
Tatsi, all day long I work to please this officer,
那个外交官、一些旅游的人 就是为了得到他们的支持
that diplomat, some tourist, to store up favors
要是当“我们”需要帮助时
so if there is a time when we need help,
我能找到能起作用的人
I have powerful people I can call upon,
可维克托是个好邻居啊
But Victor was a good neighbor,
他不是我的家人 家人才是至关重要的
He is not family, Family is all that matters,
拜托 拜托 这件事就按我说的办
Please, please, leave these things to my good judgment,
这个安排简直是胡扯
This assignment is bullshit,
拜托 在上等饭店呆着就没人能伤害我们了？
Come on, A few days in a nice hotel, no one shooting at us?
先生们 欢迎光临米尔・科林斯饭店
Gentlemen, welcome to the Mille Collines,
我是保罗・卢斯赛伯吉纳 客房经理
I am Paul Rusesabagina, the house manager,
- 你好吗？ - 很高兴见到您
- How you doing? - Nice to meet you,
有任何需要 和我说便是
Anything that you need, please find me,
- 谢谢 - 当然的
- Thank you, - Certainly,
那胡图族人和图西族人有什么区别？
So, what is the actual difference between a Hutu and a Tutsi?
按照比利时殖民者的说法
According to the Belgian colonists,
图西族人更高 且举止更为优雅
the Tutsis are taller and more elegant,
是比利时人区分的
It was the Belgians that created the division,
怎么讲？
How?
他们把鼻子较窄的、皮肤较白的人挑出来
They picked people, those with thinner noses, lighter skin,
他们曾经测量所有人鼻子的宽度
They used to measure the width of people's noses,
比利时人利用图西族人来统治国家
The Belgians used the Tutsis to run the country,
他们离开后 又把政权交给了胡图族人
Then when they left, they left the power to the Hutus,
当然胡图族人由于被镇压多年
and of course the Hutus took revenge
便对图西族的政界要人采取了报复行为
on the elite Tutsis for years of repression,
我说的对吗 保罗？
Am I telling the truth, Paul?
是的 很不幸的遭遇 请把这个给将军
Yes, unfortunately, Please take this to the general,
本尼迪克特是基加利最好的记者 这方面的专家
Benedict is our finest journalist in Kigali, an expert on the subject,
那你是哪个族的 保罗？
So what are you, Paul?
我是胡图族
I am Hutu,
先生们
Gentlemen,
- 再来点香槟？ - 很不错 再来点香槟吧
- More champagne? - More champagne would be nice,
抱歉 宝贝 能问个私人问题吗？
Excuse me, honey, Can I ask you a personal question?
- 你是胡图族还是图西族？ - 我是图西族
- Are you a Hutu or a Tutsi? - I am Tutsi,
- 你朋友呢？也是图西族？ - 不 我是胡图族
- And your friend? Tutsi? - No, I am Hutu,
还能是双胞胎
They could be twins,
去拿摄像机 将军要接见我们
Get the camera, The general's going to give us an interview,
好的
Okay,
我住22号房 我想和你继续聊聊
I'm in room 22, I'd love to finish up this conversation,
联合国高级军官声称卢旺达秘密组织了武装力量
Senior U.N. officers claim that the Rwandan army is secretly training
将胡图族民兵装备为部落民兵
and arming the Hutu militia called the Interhamwe.
就这项声明 我采访了武装力量的领袖比齐蒙戈将军
I put this claim to the head of the armed forces, General Bizimungu.
不 不 我们从未训练民兵
No. No, we have not been training the militia.
联合国对此表示指责是错误的
The U. N. are mistaken in this accusation.
你赞成总统和反叛分子签署和平协定吗？
Do you support your president's agreement to make peace with the rebels?
全军上下都支持总统的决定
The president has the full support of the army.
图西族叛军和哈比亚利马纳总统
That peace agreement will be signed today in Tanzania
将于今天在坦桑尼亚签署和平协定
between Tutsi rebel forces and President Habyarimana.
对于卢旺达 对于整个非洲来说
This is a great day for Rwanda
都是不寻常的一天
and for all of Africa,
谈判取代了双方的对峙状态
Negotiation has replaced confrontation,,,
保罗 来喝一杯
Paul, have a drink,
友谊取代了恐慌
Friendship has replaced fear,
女士们先生们 我们为和平协定的签署
Ladies and gentlemen, we have a live feed
准备了丰盛的午餐
to the signing of the peace agreement,
为我们的总统先生干杯 希望他能重现和平
To our president, May he find peace,
希望所有人都和平共处
May we all find peace,
愿我们大家都致力于维护这来之不易的协定
Let us all dedicate ourselves to nurturing this hard-earned accord,
为和平干杯！
To peace!
Peace!
你来的话 别忘了来我这儿
Look me up if you come over,
好的 这是个美丽的城市
Yes, it is a beautiful city,
我正打算回去――真抱歉
I am planning on returning there as-- Forgive me,
- 谢谢 拜 - 托马斯
- Thank you, Bye, - Thomas,
- 你好 费登丝 - 保罗
- Hello, Fedens, - Paul,
呃 这真让人吃惊
Well, this is a surprise,
抱歉 保罗 我们得谈谈
Forgive us, Paul, We must talk,
好啊 怎么了？
Yes, what's wrong?
据可靠消息称 保罗
I have it from a very reliable source, Paul,
谁？
Who?
谢谢 萨利文
Thank you, Sullivan,
我的助手 胡图族的人
My assistant, the Hutu Power man,
他说我们必须立刻离开这儿 形势马上就会变得很糟糕
He says that we must get out now, that soon it'll be very bad,
这人叫什么名字
Give me this man's name,
拜托 保罗 尽管他是部族民兵 但他是朋友
Please, Paul, even though he is lnterhamwe, he's a friend,
他是想要你的工作 托马斯
He wants your job, Thomas,
他说有个信号
He said that there is a signal,
即“砍掉高的树木”
It is "Cut the tall trees,"
一旦听到这个讯号 民兵就会投入战斗
And when they hear this signal, the militia are to go to war,
保罗 求求你了 让塔莎娜和我们走吧
Paul, please, let us take Tatiana with us,
你是胡图族 你会很安全的
You are Hutu, You will be safe,
费登丝 我知道你听到了很多传言
Fedens, I know you have heard many things,
我也知道我们看到的状况 托马斯
And I know what we have seen, Thomas,
但是拜托 联合国的人现在在这儿
But please, the United Nations are here now,
世界各地的记者都保持着关注
The world press are watching,
和平协定也都签署了 这个进程…
The peace has been signed, Let this process work--
怎么了？
What was that?
停电了
Power cuts,
我们会自行发电的
We are running on generators,
费登丝…
Fedens,,,
拜托 别担心
Please, don't worry,
明天你过来
Tomorrow you will come by the house
我们和塔莎娜商量一下
and we will discuss this with Tatiana,
好吗？
All right?
- 晚安 保罗 - 是的 代我吻吻姑娘们
- Good night, Paul, - Yes, Kiss the girls for me,
见鬼！
Shit!
呆在家里别出来 呆在家里别出来
Stay in your houses, Stay in your house,
所有人都呆在家里别出来！
Everybody stay in your house!
塔莎娜？
Tatiana?
- 保罗！ - 塔莎娜！
- Paul! - Tatiana!
- 这儿怎么回事？ - 我们的房子被烧了
- What is going on here? - Our house has been burned,
- 你没听到新闻？ - 什么新闻？
- Didn't you hear the news? - What news?
据说哈比亚利马纳总统被谋杀了
They are saying President Habyarimana has been murdered,
图西族反叛分子干的
Tutsi rebels have killed him,
瞎说 总统是去签署和平协定的 怎么会被反叛分子谋杀？
Nonsense, Why would the rebels kill the president when he agreed to peace?
各位 拜托 别呆在这儿 拜托
Everyone, please, out of this room, Please,
吉恩・巴提斯 让他们到别的房间去坐
Jean Baptiste, find them seats in the other room,
奥德特 拜托
Odette, please,
- 你见到托马斯和费登丝了？ - 不错 我让他们回家去
- Did you meet with Thomas and Fedens? - Yes, I told them to go home,
- 去给他们打个电话 塔莎 - 我试过了 电话…不能用
- Go and call them, Tatsi, - I've tried, Our phones, they do not work,
为什么邻居都跑到我们家来？
Why do the neighbors run to us?
你是他们唯一能信任的胡图族人
You are the only Hutu they can trust,
但你是图西族啊
You are a Tutsi,
他们很害怕 保罗 我也很害怕
They are scared, Paul, I am scared,
这可能是煽动者放出的谣言
These are probably rumors started by agitators,
为了孩子们 我们必须保持平静 塔莎 我们必须这样
We must remain calm for the children, Tatsi, We must,
抱歉 保罗 伊利说罗杰走了
Forgive me, Paul, Elys says that Roger has gone,
走了？去哪儿了？
Gone? Gone where?
- 他担心他的朋友西蒙 妈妈 - 他去哪儿了 伊利？
- He was afraid for his friend Simon, Mama, - Where has he gone, Elys?
去隔壁了
He went next door,
等等 保罗！
Wait, Paul!
塔莎娜 别来 你去和孩子们呆着
Tatiana, no, You have to stay here with the children,
- 到屋里去 别出来！ - 拜托
- Stay in the house, No! - Please,
保罗 拜托 怎么了？给我说 怎么了？
Paul, please, what is wrong? Tell me, what is wrong?
- 噢 儿子！你哪儿受伤了？ - 他还好吗？噢 宝贝！
- Oh, my son! Where are you hurt? - Is he okay? Oh, my baby!
告诉我 哪儿受伤了？
Talk to me, Where are you hurt?
保罗？
Paul?
噢 塔莎,
Oh, Tatsi,
奥德特 奥德特！
Odette, Odette!
噢 不
Oh, no,
我没事
I'm okay,
脱掉他的衣服 塔莎 弄点水来
Get his clothes off, Tatsi, please get some water,
- 他受伤了 - 拜托 把他的衣服脱下来
- He's hurt, - Please, let's get his clothes off,
- 他身上都是血 - 躺下 孩子
- He's covered in blood, - Lay back, son,
他去隔壁齐朗戈家了
He went next door to the Chirangas,
他哪儿受伤了？
Where is he hurt?
看这儿 奥德特 看看这儿
Look here, Odette, look here,
别动 罗杰 让他别动 保罗
Stay still, Roger, Keep him still, Paul,
- 我找不到伤口 - 你怎么了？
- I can't find the wound, - What happened to you?
- 告诉你妈妈 - 告诉我
- Tell your mother, - Talk to me,
给你妈妈说怎么了 罗杰
Tell your mother what happened, Roger,
罗杰 会没事的
Roger, you're okay,
别担心 他没受伤 他没受伤
Do not worry, he is not cut, He is not hurt,
这不是他的血 保罗
This is not his blood, Paul,
你没有受伤
You are not hurt,
亲爱的 没事儿 没事了
My darling, it's okay, It's okay,
安全了 看着妈妈
You are safe, Look at your mother,
过来 伊利
Come here, Elys,
- 这些血哪儿来的？ - 拜托 拜托！
- Where did the blood come from? - Please, please!
- 安全了 - 你出去了 罗杰
- You are safe, - You are out, Roger,
安全了 安全了 罗杰 安全了 罗杰
You are safe, you are safe, Roger, You are safe, Roger,
没事了
It's okay,
我爱你 爱你
I love you so much, I love you,
噢 儿子
Oh, son,
保罗
Paul,
卢旺达善良的人们 听我说 可怕的消息…
Listen to me, good people of Rwanda. Terrible news...
- 是真的 - 恐怖的新闻…
- It is true, - Horrible news...
我们伟大的总统被蟑螂一般的图西族人谋杀了
Our great president is murdered by the Tutsi cockroaches.
噢 上帝！
Oh, my God!
他们诱骗他去签署假和约
They tricked him to sign their phony peace agreement.
然后在空中击中了他的飞机
Then they shot his plane from the sky.
算账的时候到了 优秀的卢旺达胡图族人
It is time to clear the brush, good Hutus of Rwanda.
我们必须砍倒高的树木
We must cut the tall trees.
立即砍倒高的树木！
Cut the tall trees now!
有士兵来了！
The soldiers are here!
- 我们开始努力吧 忠诚的胡图族人 - 不 不
- Let us go to work, loyal Hutus. - No, no,
各位 保持平静 保持平静 安静下来
Everyone, stay calm, Stay calm and be quiet,
找出这些叛国者 一个都别放过
Find these traitors. Let none of them escape.
走开 所有人都出来
Split up, Everybody out,
- 你们两个 去看看后面 - 快去
- You two, check the back, - Go,
- 你 去找他 - 是 先生
- You, go and find him, - Yes, sir,
我得去和他们谈谈
I better go have a word with them,
去后面看看 别让人跑了
Go around the back, Make sure no one comes out,
是 先生！
Yes, sir!
你们谁负责？
Who's in charge here?
你
You,
- 能帮上什么忙吗 先生？ - 所有人都出来！出来！
- Can I help you, sir? - Everybody out! Out!
- 身份证拿出来看看 - 拿着东西 快走！
- Let me see your identity card, - Grab your things, Go!
我是比齐蒙戈将军的好朋友
I am a good friend of General Bizimungu,
出来！
Get out!
Get out of here!
所有人都出来！出来 出来！
Everybody, out! Get out, get out!
你在外事饭店工作？
You work at the Hotel Diplomat?
不 我在米尔・科林斯饭店工作
No, I work at the Mille Collines,
我以前在外事饭店工作
I used to work at the Diplomat,
我们要使用饭店 所有的房门钥匙都被锁在保险柜里
We want to use that hotel, All the room keys are in the safe,
你去把它打开 我们走
You must open it, Let's go,
- 保罗！ - 先生 我不能撇下家人不管
- Paul! - Sir, I cannot leave my family,
我要带上他们 这儿不安全
I must take them with me, It is not safe here,
到处都是图西族间谍
There are Tutsi spies everywhere,
我不会让你都带上
I cannot take all these people,
不 不 先生 不要紧的
No, no, sir, you do not have to,
我们有轿车 也有货车
We have our car and our van,
- 卡里索上尉 快过来 - 收到
- Captain Kaliso, come on. - Roger,
- 我们走！ - 快来 快！走 走
- Let's go! - Come on, Hurry! Go around, go around,
搜查到了 走 走！
We found him, Let's go, Let's go!
- 我能和你一起吗？ - 可以 当然 耶利米 快
- Can I go with you? - Yes, of course, Jeremiah, Hurry,
噢 上帝 不！
Oh, Jesus, no!
噢 是西蒙 爸爸！
Oh, it's Simon, Papa!
别看 别看 别看 别看 塔莎娜
Don't look, don't look, don't look, Don't look, Tatiana,
- 保险柜在经理办公室 - 你们俩 和他一起去
- The safe is in the manager's office, - You two, go with him,
看看这个 啤酒
Look at this, Beer,
拿到了
I've got them,
蹲下 所有人都蹲下！
Get down, all of you!
先生 先生 这儿 拿到了 我拿到了 我拿到了
Sir, sir, Here, I have them, I have them, I've got them,
叛国者！
Traitor!
这些都是图西族蟑螂！
These are Tutsi cockroaches!
让我解释 先生 拜托等等
Let me explain, sir, Please wait,
开枪
Shoot them,
求求你了 我不会用枪 不会
Please, I don't use guns, I don't,
很简单
It's easy,
开枪 不然你就先去死
Shoot them, or you die first,
先生 我给你多少钱才能不杀他们？
Sir, what could I pay you not to do this?
给我钱？
You wanna pay me?
为什么不呢？看看他们
Why not? Look at them,
他们不是反叛分子
These are not rebels,
对你来说他们马上就失去价值了
Soon they will be worthless to you,
为什么不在执行任务时赚点钱呢？
Why not take some money for your work?
- 多少？ - 你开个价吧
- How much? - You name a price,
每个人10,000法郎
10,000 francs for each,
- 先生 我没那么多钱啊 - 好吧
- Sir, I don't have that much, - Okay,
等等 等等！这儿
Wait, wait! Here,
这是1,000美金 还有这个
It's 1,000 U,S, And here,
我妻子和孩子们的50,000法郎
50,000 francs for my wife and children,
- 带他们走 - 走 走 走
- Take them, - Go, go, go,
走 走 走
Go, go, go,
- 你还有钱吗？ - 没有了
- Have you any money? - Nothing,
- 保罗 别扔下他们 - 上车去
- Paul, don't let them die, - Get in the van,
先生 其实我还有些钱
Sir, I have more money actually,
再让他们给你点东西 钱啊之类的 看看他们有些什么
And let them give you something, Some money, whatever they have,
好吗？
All right?
- 给你 - 把你们有的都给我
Here you are, Give me everything you have,
来 保罗 就这些了
Here, Paul, it's all I have,
都给你 好吗？
Here you are, See?
这些就够一只蟑螂 挑一个吧
This is enough for one cockroach, Pick one,
先生…
Sir,,,
我给你100,000法郎 你把他们都放了
I will give you 100,000 francs for all of them,
- 给我啊 - 我没带在身上
- Give me it, - I don't have it here,
在米尔・科林斯饭店 我可以去拿
At the Mille Collines I can get it for you,
你会逃进饭店 投靠联合国的人
You'll run into the hotel and hide behind the U,N,
先生 我发誓 100,000法郎
Sir, I swear, 100,000 francs,
我会给你钱的 他们还留在外面
I will get you the money, You keep them outside,
求求你了 先生 求求你了
Please, sir, Please,
- 走吧 - 好了 大家都上车去
- Let's go, - Okay, Everyone in the van,
快点 快
Come on now, Hurry,
和我的士兵一起去 快点回来
Go with my soldiers, And hurry back
要是想保住这些蟑螂的话
if you want to keep these cockroaches,
士兵来了 车呢？
The soldiers are here, Where is the car?
- 我无能为力 - 抱歉 先生！拜托 你能…
There is nothing I can do, Excuse me, sir! Please, could you--
给你钱
Here's the money,
100,000法郎一文不少
100,000 francs as promised,
拜托了 让他们走吧 先生
Now please, let them go, sir,
钱先拿着 我们稍候再来拿
Take the money, We will get them later,
- 你可以走了 - 谢谢
- You can go, - Thank you,
叛国者
Traitor,
谢谢了 保罗
Thank you, Paul,
你明白吗 杜比？我不能等保罗了
Do you understand, Dube? Because I can't wait for Paul,
- 他来了你告诉他… - 他来了 先生
- You must tell him when he comes-- - Here he is, sir,
保罗 我得走了 基韦・洛奇的人都逃走了
Paul, I have to go, The staff of Kivu Lodge have fled,
我必须关门了 一切交给你负责了
I have to close up there, You are in charge now,
好的 好
It's okay, it's okay,
昨晚卢旺达首都基加利的空难无一人生还
There were no survivors in last night's plane crash in Kigali, Rwanda.
大家都靠边站 把门让出来
Everyone, please move to the side, Clear the door,
来 塔莎
Come, Tatsi,
安德烈 我要两件套房
Andre, I need two suites,
- 保罗 拜托 我的护照呢？ - 好的 我明白了
- Paul, please, where is my passport? - Yes, I understand,
我要和大使馆联系一下
I need to get hold of my embassy.
请稍等片刻
If you give me one moment, please,
奥德特 吉恩・巴提斯 去这个房间
Odette, Jean Baptiste, take this room.
我们的邻居怎么办？
What about our neighbors?
他们干什么？
What will they do?
- 杜比 - 在 先生？
- Dube, - Yes, sir?
拜托…把这些“客人”安排到两个工作间
Please,,,put these "guests" in two staff rooms,
马上 先生
Right away, sir,
不 不 不 拜托 那不新鲜 吃这个水果
No, no, no, Please, it's old, Have the fruit,
没事了 罗杰 没事了 我们就呆在这儿
It's all right, Roger, It's all right, We're here,
- 啊 约瑟夫 - 你的衣服 先生
- Ah, Joseph, - Your suit, sir,
真让人无法容忍
This mess is unacceptable,
给管委会打个电话 让他们马上过来 谢谢
Call housekeeping, get them up here right away, Thank you,
- 我给托马斯和费登丝打个电话 - 好的
- I'm trying Thomas and Fedens, - All right,
接线员 我想拨外线
Operator, I need a line,
我现在想拨外线 拜托 喂？
I need a line now, Please, Hello?
没打通？
You did not reach them?
没有 没反应
No, No answer,
局势很紧张 我们只想告诉那儿的千家万户
It is a very tense situation, and I just want to assure the families
我们会尽一切努力
of those who are there that we are doing everything we possibly can
确保居民的安全
to try to ensure the safety of our citizens there.
你至少得告诉我们 机场还开放吗？
Can you at least tell us, is the airport actually open?
我们会和机场联系 我们也会和大使馆联系
We are calling the airport, We are calling the embassy,
我们会尽可能给你们更多的信息
We are trying to get as much information for you as we can,
- 是的 你的护照 是的 - 我的护照
- And yes, your passport, yes, - And my passport,
安托瓦内特会为你处理此事
Antoinette will take care of this for you,
杜比 格莱戈瓦呢？
Dube, where is Gregoire?
先生 他搬进了总统套房
Sir, he has moved into the Presidential Suite,
经理先生
Mr, Manager,
你觉得你在干什么 格莱戈瓦？
What do you think you are doing, Gregoire?
谁啊？
Who is it?
没事儿 亲爱的
It's okay, darling,
你要干什么？
What do you want?
你最好离开这间房间 马上回楼下去
You had better get out of this room and back downstairs right away,
- 我不再听你的了 - 好 不听我的
- I don't have to listen to you anymore, - Yes, you do,
现在有我负责 立刻离开这间房间
I am in charge, Now get out of this room right now,
经理先生 有嗅到蟑螂的味道吗？
Mr, Manager, do you notice the smell of cockroaches?
要是我离开这间房间 我敢保证能找得到
If I were to leave this room, I'm sure I could find it,
而且我认识人可以清除他们
And I know people who can cleanse it,
但或许不会干涉到你 为什么要这样？
But maybe it doesn't bother you, Why is that?
你习惯了这个味道？
Are you used to the smell?
呃 我不太习惯
Well, not me,
我要打扫房间清除它
I need a clean room to escape it,
拜托搬到饭店去 各位 继续搬
Please move into the hotel, Everyone, keep moving,
我的房子被焚烧了 我无家可归
My house has been burned, I have nowhere to go,
是的 我理解 阁下
Yes, I understand this, Your Honor,
但我们正在腾房间
But we are operating at capacity as it is,
我可以给你一个房间 但你们只能一起使用 抱歉
I can give you one room, but you will have to share it, I'm sorry,
- 我们没法一起使用 - 抱歉 我很抱歉
- There's no way we can share, - I am sorry, Forgive me,
我们有八个人呢
There are eight of us,
- 怎么了？ - 保罗 来帮帮我
- Yes? - Paul, I need your help,
好 阿彻夫人
Yes, Madame Archer,
他们是圣弗朗西斯孤儿院的图西族儿童
They're Tutsi children from the St, Francis orphanage,
好了 来 我们走
Okay, come on, let's go,
- 我只剩一个房间了 - 没关系的
- I have only one room, - That'll do,
来
Come,
- 奥托 拜托 - 抱歉
- Otto, please, - Excuse me,
下士 请帮女士拎拎包 快点
Corporal, take that lady's bag, please, and quickly,
- 我必须去接剩下的 - 剩下的？
- Have to go get the rest of them, - The rest of them?
还有十个 我马上回来
There are another ten, I'll be back soon,
阿彻夫人
Madame Archer,
我想请您帮个忙
I have a favor to ask of you,
我爱人的哥哥家 住在圣弗朗西斯附近
My brother-in-law and his family, they live near the St, Francis,
奥克莱尔街 20号
On O'Clare, 20,
您能帮忙带他们来吗？
Can you please get them and bring them here to me?
- 没问题 - 我有照片
- Sure, - And I have a photo,
拜托 继续搬！
Please, keep moving!
- 谢谢 保罗 - 谢谢
- Thanks, Paul, - Thank you,
谢谢搬进饭店！
Please move into the hotel!
过来 孩子们 别害怕
Come on, kids, don't be afraid,
- 带他们去后面 - 大伙儿 继续！
- Take them around the back, - Everyone, keep moving!
他说话了吗？
Has he spoken to you yet?
没有
No,
你的脸上还是挂满了惆怅？
Is your face still hurting?
没事儿
It's all right,
邻居们叫我替他们对你的仁慈道谢
The neighbors asked me to thank you for your kindness,
我不应该带他们来这儿
I shouldn't have brought them here,
我得到职位时第一件被叮嘱的事就是
The first thing they told me when I received my appointment
绝对、绝对不能降低饭店的品质
was to never, never lower the tone of the hotel,
“一直要维持米尔・科林斯饭店的尊贵形象 保罗”
"Maintain the Mille Collines' dignity at all times, Paul,"
这一切很快就会过去的
Soon all of this will be over,
要是我失去了工作怎么办 塔莎？
What if I lose my job, Tatsi?
噢 上帝！
Oh, my God!
- 你去哪儿？ - 我马上回来
- Where are you going? - I'll be right back,
照顾好他们
Take care of them,
怎么做 先生？
How, sir?
给他们洗澡 让他们吃东西
Bathe them, feed them,
哄他们睡觉
Put them to bed,
有事请我会帮你忙的
I will send you some help,
好了 宝贝们
Okay, babies,
我们听说了报复性屠杀的行动
We have heard reports of reprisal massacres,
联合国会出面制止流血事件的发生吗？
Will the U,N, intervene to stop the bloodshed?
我们来这儿是为了维持和平 而非创造和平
We're here as peacekeepers, not as peacemakers,
我下令不得对此加以干涉
My orders are not to intervene,
- 抱歉 - 谢谢 上校
- Excuse me, - Thank you, Colonel,
这儿 过来
Here, Over here,
听着 我弄了辆车 我们必须马上离开
Listen, I got us a car, but we gotta move now,
我们不能那样做 杰克
We're not allowed to do that, Jack,
大卫 那些该死的东西会把墙推倒 我们必须有所防备
David, the shit's going down outside these walls, We gotta cover it,
我们不会离开饭店的 除非有装甲车
We're not leaving the hotel grounds unless we have an armored car,
- 这是章程 - 章程？
- That's the ground rules, - The ground rules?
你以为我们这是在哪儿？他妈的温布尔登吗？
Where do you think we are, fucking Wimbledon?
就此作罢 直到弄到合适的交通工具 杰克
We cover the story from here until we get the proper vehicles, Jack,
去拍摄些名单B中的难民吧
Shoot some "B" roll of the refugees,
我们走
Let's go,
上校 我无法确保这些人的安全
Colonel, I have no way to protect these people,
我这儿的房间装不下这么多难民
And I have more refugees than I have room for as it is,
红十字会今天带来了20名孤儿
I was given 20 orphans today by the Red Cross,
这儿不是难民营
This is not a refugee camp,
你不能把他们带去你那儿吗？
Can you not take them with you to your facilities?
不行 我不能那样 保罗 抱歉
No, I can't do that, Paul, I'm sorry,
我的难民营很令人担忧
I'm overwhelmed at my refugee camp,
那儿一直在打仗 持续的战斗
I'm under attack, constant attack,
一旦我们控制住局势 我就带他们去那儿
As soon as we can stabilize this situation, then I'll take 'em,
…防止那些试图逃脱审判的图西族蟑螂
...and stop the Tutsi cockroaches who try to run from justice.
一名叫马吉萨的图西族法官躲在4个…
The Tutsi cockroach judge called Makesa is hiding at 4...
- …喀布尔和他的同伙… - 关掉收音机
-... Kabulla and his cockroaches... - Turn that radio off,
他的情况将被密切关注 他…
Watch out for him. He--
回去工作 我们必须让饭店正常运作
And get back to work, We have a hotel to run,
这儿没什么好干的了 老板都走了
There's no work here anyway, The boss has left,
我就是你们的老板！
I am your boss!
先生 卢旺达米尔・科林斯饭店来电 一号线
Sir, there's a call from the Mille Collines in Rwanda on line one.
什么？你哪位？
Yes? Who am I speaking to?
是的 先生 我是保罗・卢斯赛伯吉纳 客房经理
Yes, sir, Paul Rusesabagina, the house manager,
上次你来这儿是我们见过面 提伦斯先生
I met you on your last visit here, Mr, Tillens,
啊 是的 保罗 我记得
Ah, yes, Paul, I remember,
情况怎么样了？
How are things there?
很复杂 先生
The situation is difficult, sir.
有部分董事觉得我们应该关闭米尔・科林斯饭店
Some of our directors believe we should close the Mille Collines
直到动荡的局面结束
until this unrest is over,
我对此拿不定主意 保罗 你觉得呢？
I'm not sure about that, Paul. What do you think?
先生 那会对我们的声誉造成不良影响
Sir, that would be very bad for our reputation,
米尔・科林斯饭店对于忠实的消费者来说就是一片平静的绿洲
The Mille Collines is an oasis of calm for all our loyal customers,
比利时航空公司弃之不顾 他们会怎么想？
What would they think if Sabena deserted them now?
我想你保证 联合国已经控制了一切 先生
I assure you, the United Nations have everything under control, sir,
很好 保罗 很好
Very well, Paul, Very well,
但如果形势变得更严峻 我们还得关闭
But if this thing gets worse, we must close,
要是有什么需要我帮忙的 给我电话
If there is anything I can do, please call,
先生 是的 我现在正有一件事需要你帮忙
Sir, yes, there is one thing I'm going to be needing from you right away,
告诉大家 我这样请求大家显得很尴尬
Let me tell you, it was an embarrassment for me to have to ask for this,
在场的大多数人都相互认识
Most of us in this room have known each other
并在一起共事多年
and worked together for many years,
真的需要我致函比利时方面
Is it really necessary for me to get a letter from Belgium
来让你们继续工作吗？
for you to perform your duties?
实际上 别在乎这封信
In fact, forget this letter,
要是你们不想为我工作
If you don't want to work for me and
而情愿出去 那现在就离开吧
would rather be out there, then leave now,
拜托 各位 回到工作岗位上去
Please, everyone, back to work,
保罗 感谢你来
Paul, thank you for coming,
空调不能用了
The air conditioner's on the blink,
你能帮我看看吗？
is there any way you can have a look at it?
- 这是我最后一天了 - 当然
- I'm just on a deadline, - Certainly,
弗雷德 告诉我你何时收到卫星信号的 谢谢
Fred, let me know when you get the satellite feed, Thanks,
弗莱明先生 我还给你带了些茶叶来 先生
Mr, Fleming, I brought you some tea as well, sir,
谢谢 保罗
Thank you, Paul,
你是沙漠里的一片绿洲
You're an oasis in the desert,
…政府和军队的人
...the elements of the government and army
正在效仿索马里的美国人的做法
are following the example of what happened to the Americans in Somalia.
我认为他们意欲胁迫我们 试图袭击我们…
I think they intend to intimidate us, try to attack us, and...
希望西方能考虑撤军
hope that the West will pull all its troops out.
- 你认为他们会成功吗？ - 不 当然不会
- Do you think they'll succeed? - No, they won't.
联合国维和部队就驻扎在这儿
The U. N. 's here to stay.
总统的飞机被击落后
What about the outbreak of violence
暴力事件的情况如何？
since the shooting down of the president's plane?
你到底在干什么？
What the hell do you think you're doing?
我要对这些人的安全负责
I'm responsible for the safety of this crew,
什么？
What is this?
- 哪儿拍的？ - 沿途半英里处
- Where did you get this? - Half a mile down the road,
弗雷德 我是大卫
Fred, it's David,
我拿到了让人难以置信的录像 关于集体屠杀
I've got incredible footage, It's a massacre,
死尸 以及弯刀
Dead bodies, machetes,
如果我立即赶过去 你能播报晚间新闻吗？
If I get this through right away, can you make the evening news?
好
Yeah,
这个必须头条播报
You have to lead with this,
我是说你 你来试试看
I point at you, you do a shot,
你会得到两倍的偿还 看看是否所有的酒…
And you'll get a total double and see if all the drinking--
- 抱歉 达格里什先生 - 嘿 保罗
- Excuse me, Mr, Daglish, - Hey, Paul,
听我说 之前的事很抱歉
Listen, sorry about earlier,
如果我知道你在那儿 我就不会…
If I'd known you were in there, I wouldn't have--
你拍下这段录像我很高兴 全世界都能看到
I am glad that you have shot this footage and that the world will see it,
这是我们有机会让人干涉的唯一办法
It is the only way we have a chance that people might intervene,
不错 但要是没人来干涉 披露这些还会是好事吗？
Yeah, and if no one intervenes, is it still a good thing to show?
人们看到这种暴行 怎么会不干涉呢？
How can they not intervene when they witness such atrocities?
我认为如果人们看到这些录像…
I think if people see this footage,,,
…他们会说 “噢 上帝 太恐怖了”
,,,they'll say, "Oh, my God, that's horrible,"
然后便继续享用他们的晚餐
and then go on eating their dinners,
我到底在想什么？听着 想去放松一下吗？
What the hell do I know? Listen, you wanna just relax?
我还有事情要做 谢谢你的邀请
I have more work to do, I thank you for your offer,
祝你晚上过得愉快 达格里什先生
Please enjoy your evening, Mr, Daglish,
- 救命啊！请救救我们！求求你们了！ - 先生！先生！
- Help! Please help us! Please! - Sir! Sir!
门口出事了
We've got trouble at the gate,
请问这儿有医疗援助吗？
Can we have some medical assistance here, please?
那群人 跟我来 离开那个地方
That group, come with me, Move out of the area,
- 到这边来 起来 起来 - 好了 所有人都后退
- Here, get up, get up, - Right, fall back, everybody,
本尼迪克特 怎么回事？
Benedict, what is happening?
他们杀了所有人 妇女…
They're killing everyone, The lady,,,
部族民兵包围了整个城市
The lnterhamwe have surrounded the whole town,
快！
Come on!
开路 马上
Cover the road, Now,
站好岗
Stand your ground,
坚持
Hold the line,
别开枪！别开枪！
Do not shoot! Do not shoot!
- 中尉 去看着门口 - 是 先生
- Lieutenant, guard this gate, - Yes, sir,
你们俩 到沙袋后面去
You two, take up positions behind those sandbags,
他们杀了我们的人 维和部队死了十个比利时士兵
They murdered my men, I lost ten Belgian U,N, soldiers,
他们是在保护女首相的安全
They were protecting the lady prime minister,
- 她死了？ - 不错 死了
- She is dead? - Yeah, she's dead,
欧洲人正在集结武装准备干涉
The Europeans are putting together an intervention force,
几天后就能抵达
They'll be here in a few days,
我明白 上校
I understand that, Colonel,
但这些人我没办法安置了
but there is simply no place for me to put all of them,
我能怎么办？
What can I do?
我会再派两个人去门上 都是我最好的中尉
I'll put two more men on the gate, two of my best lieutenants,
- 好吧 - 好
- All right, - All right,
我知道了 谢谢
I understand, Thank you,
阿彻夫人
Madame Archer,
你好
Hello,
- 我们五天前就一直等着你 - 抱歉
- We were expecting you five days ago, - I'm sorry,
我哥哥的家人 你找到了吗？
My brother and his family, did you find them?
我到了他们的住处 但屋里没人
I made it to the house, but it was empty,
- 没人？ - 一定是被搜查过了
- Empty? - It had been ransacked,
我走的时候 一位老太太朝我招手
As I left, an old woman, she waved to me,
我去了她家 有两个小女孩 她们都很安全
I went to the house, She has the two little girls, They're safe,
好
Okay,
但是…
But,,,
我哥哥和他妻子…那个老太太知道他们的下落吗？
My brother and his wife-- did the old lady know of them?
我哥哥一定死了 他们不会留下孩子们的
My brother is dead, They would never leave their children,
或许他们没有回家 塔莎娜 他们藏起来了
Perhaps they could not make it home, Tatiana, They are hiding,
拜托 您能回去帮我把女孩们带过来吗？
Please, can you return and bring the girls back here to us?
不行 到处都是部落民兵设置的路障
I can't, There are lnterhamwe roadblocks everywhere,
当我到达孤儿院…
When I reached the orphanage,,,
…部落民兵也在那儿
,,,the lnterhamwe were there,
他们已经开始杀戮孩子
They'd already started killing children,
他们让我看
They made me watch,
有个女孩
There was one girl,
他背上绑着个小妹妹
she had her little sister wrapped on her back,
他们朝她砍去的一瞬间 她朝我大喊
As they were about to chop her, she cried out to me,
“求求你别让他们杀我
"Please don't let them kill me,
我发誓我再也不做图西族人了”
I promise I won't be Tutsi anymore,"
拜托 我不能
Please, I can't,
他们的目标就是图西族的孩子
They're targeting Tutsi children,
保罗 他们要将下一代铲除干净
Paul, to wipe out the next generation,
我带着孤儿不知该去何处 保罗
I've nowhere to take the orphans, Paul,
别担心了 马上就会有武装力量来干涉了
Don't worry, There will be an intervention force coming soon,
到时候再让孤儿们出去
We will get the orphans out then,
他们来了！
They're here!
他们来了！我们安全了！
They're here! We are safe!
士兵们来了！
Soldiers have arrived!
- 哇噢 看看 是法国人！ - 是的！
- Wow, look, it's the French! - Yes!
感谢上帝！
Thank goodness!
- 欢迎 - 谢谢
- Welcome, - Thank you,
干得好
Well done,
时间差不多了 先生们
About time, gentlemen,
谢谢你救了我们
Thank you for saving our lives,
好了 罗杰
It's okay, Roger,
吉恩・巴提斯 我们的祈祷终于奏效了 感谢上帝
Jean Baptiste, our prayers have been answered, Thank God,
是的 终于！
Yes, finally!
瞧 都好了
See, it's okay,
我方无能为力
We can do nothing from our side,
甜心 我告诉过你我们会安全的
Sweetheart, I told you we'd be safe,
看见了吗？我说过的 是的
See? I told you, Yeah,
上校 需要点什么？
So, Colonel, what can I get for you?
性子烈点的
Something strong,
- 苏格兰威士忌？ - 不错
- Scotch? - Yeah,
祝贺你 上校
Congratulations, Colonel,
你创造了一个奇迹
You have performed a minor miracle,
- 祝贺 嗯？ - 是的 先生
- Congratulations, huh? - Yes, sir,
你应该朝我吐唾沫才对
You should spit in my face,
抱歉 上校？
Excuse me, Colonel?
你很卑鄙
You're dirt,
我们觉得你很卑鄙 保罗
We think you're dirt, Paul,
“我们”是指？
Who is "we"?
西方 西方列强 你信仰的一切 保罗
The West, all the superpowers, everything you believe in, Paul,
他们都认为你卑鄙 认为你丑陋 无用
They think you're dirt, they think you're dung, You're worthless,
我不太明白你在说什么 先生
I'm afraid I don't understand what you are saying, sir,
拜托 别骗我了 保罗
Come on, don't bullshit me, Paul,
你是这儿最聪明的人
You're the smartest man here,
你让他们都受你控制
You got them all eating out of your hands,
你可以拥有这个该死的饭店 除了一件东西…
You could own this freakin' hotel, except for one thing--
你是黑人
you're black,
甚至可以说 你不是个黑鬼
You're not even a nigger,
你是一个非洲人
You're an African,
他们不会呆在这儿的 保罗
They're not gonna stay, Paul,
杀戮不会停止的
They're not gonna stop this slaughter,
拜托
Please,
知道了
Got it,
- 嗨 - 嗨 爸爸
- Hello, - Hello, Daddy,
伊利 带黛安去另一间房间
Elys, take Diane in the other room,
怎么了？
What is it?
所有白人都离开了
All the whites are leaving,
他们都在撤退
They are being evacuated,
但…我们呢？
But,,,what about us?
我们被遗弃了
We have been abandoned,
士兵会制止杀戮者的啊
But the soldiers will stop the killers,
听着 听我说 塔莎 听着
Listen, Listen to me, Tatsi, Listen,
我都说了所有的白人都会离开…法国人、意大利人、
I said all the whites are leaving-- the French, the ltalians,
甚至维和部队的比利时士兵 所有人！
even the U,N, Belgian soldiers, all of them!
那谁会留下来？
Who is left?
不知道
I don't know,
奥利弗上校说整个国家维和部队共有300人
Colonel Oliver said he has 300 U,N, peacekeepers for the whole country,
他最多能抽出四个人来保护饭店安全
The most he can spare for the hotel are four men,
而且他们不允许开枪
And they are not allowed to shoot,
我真是个傻瓜
I am a fool,
不 不 不
No, No, no,
他们说我是其中之一 而我…
They told me I was one of them, and l,,,
白酒、巧克力、雪茄、体面…我都可以不要
Wine, chocolates, cigars, style-- I swallowed it,
都不要 一切都可以不要
I swallowed it, I swallowed all of it,
他们要我掌管他们的饭店
And they handed me their shit,
我没有这方面的历史 没有经历
I have no history, I have no memory,
我真是个傻瓜 塔莎
I'm a fool, Tatsi,
你不傻
You are no fool,
我了解你
I know who you are,
非洲新闻播报
News Service Africa.
据联合国方面报道
A United Nations source reports that
安全委员会的英美代表将游说
the U.S. and British representatives on the Security Council will lobby for the removal
所有维和部队撤离卢旺达
of all U. N. peacekeepers from Rwanda.
拜托 杰克 别走
Please, Jack, Please don't go,
等等 他是英国人 护照给我看看
Wait, he's British, Take out your passport,
杰克 别扔下我
Jack, please don't leave me,
我们能谈谈吗？就一分钟
Can we talk? Just one second,
求求你了 杰克 求求你了
Please, Jack, Please,
他们会把我拉到街上 会用刀砍我
They'll put me on the street, They'll chop me,
这个 拿着…
Here, Now just take,,,
- 拿着这个 - 不 不要…
- Take this, - No, no,,,
拿着这些钱 拜托 拿着
Just take the money, Please, just take the money,
你必须去 一定要去 拜托 他们正等着
You must go, You must, Please, they are waiting,
- 保罗！ - 他们等着你
- Paul! - They are waiting,
保罗
Paul,
他不会让你出去的 这个 她想要什么就给她买什么
He won't put you out, Here, give her anything she wants,
- 什么都行 付钱就是了 - 这不必了吧
- Anything, Just charge it, - This is not necessary,
- 他们会来这儿杀了我们的 - 让他走吧
- They're gonna kill us here, - Let him go,
我们得让他走
We have to let him go,
别那样 拜托
Don't do that, please,
上帝 我很惭愧
Jesus Christ, I'm so ashamed,
等等！等等！
Wait! Wait!
别开车！
Hold the buses!
彼得！
Peter!
感谢你们来这儿 非常感谢 谢谢你们
Thank you for being here, Thank you very much, Thank you,
- 卢旺达人不行 - 什么？
- No Rwandans, - What?
只许外国人 抱歉 神父 这是命令
Foreign nationals only, Sorry, Father, those were the orders,
你们不能留下这些孩子
But you can't leave the children behind.
抱歉 神父 我们得服从命令
Sorry, Father, we have our orders,
- 你们不能留下他们！ - 我们帮不上什么忙
- You can't leave them! - We can do no more,
神父 没用的
Father, it is of no use,
这些人来这儿…来这儿不是帮我们的
These men are not here-- They are not here to help us,
拜托 我们无能为力
Please, there is nothing we can do,
让你的人呆在车上 我会照顾其他人的
Get your people on the bus, I will take care of the others,
无济于事的 神父 拜托 快
It is of no use, Father, Please, hurry,
不 不 不 不 不 不 不
No, no, no, No, no, no, No,
去饭店 去饭店
To the hotel, To the hotel,
先生 拜托 别碰摄像机 我们有摄像的权力
Sir, please, don't touch the camera, We have the right to film,
- 不许摄像 - 快去饭店
- No filming, - Go to the hotel,
进去吧
Go inside,
进饭店里去 大家都去
Go inside the hotel, all of you,
是的 你们可以留下 是的 我们会照顾你们
Yes, you can stay, yes, We will take care of you,
到饭店里面去
Go into the hotel,
不！
No!
到饭店里面去 进去 饭店里面去
Go to the hotel, Go inside, Go inside the hotel,
抱歉 抱歉
Excuse me, Excuse me,
- 先生 - 来 杜比
- Sir, - Come, Dube,
- 拜托 大家都进去 - 拜托 各位 都进去吧
- Please, everyone inside, - Please, people, let's go inside,
别淋雨 拜托 来 老姐 来
Out of the rain, please, Come, sister, come,
保罗
Paul,
我想你去
I want you to go,
去哪儿？
Go where?
你带着孩子 去接女孩们
You take the children, You go get the girls,
- 你身份证上是胡图族的… - 你在说什么啊？
- Your card says Hutu-- - What are you saying?
拜托 拜托 遇到路障你就给他们钱
Please, please, You pay money at the roadblocks,
我要你去
I want you to go,
不 塔莎娜 不
No, Tatiana, no,
我不会离开你的
I will never leave you,
噢 塔莎
Oh, Tatsi,
我们睡觉 我的爱人 我们睡觉
Let us sleep, my wife, Let us sleep,
起来 起来
Get up, Get up,
起来 起来 起来
Get up, get up, get up,
- 你是经理？ - 是的 先生 怎么？
- Are you the manager? - Yes, sir, What's the matter?
所有人都马上离开饭店
Everyone must leave the hotel now,
- 什么？ - 爸爸 怎么了？
- Why? - Papa, what's wrong?
这是命令
It's an order,
我需要点时间…20、30分钟…洗个澡
I need some time-- 20, 30 minutes--to take a shower,
- 先生 人们都还在睡觉呢 - 这我管不着
- Sir, people are still sleeping, - I don't care,
拜托 我给你们那点啤酒 你们先喝着
Please, let me get you some beers, You and your boys,
我会马上下来 好吗？我会尽快
And I'll be down right away, all right? As quick as I can,
- 给你十分钟时间 - 好的 先生 十分钟
- Ten minutes, - Yes, sir, ten minutes,
- 散开 - 快 孩子们 快
- Get out of the way, - Quick, children, quickly,
- 罗杰不在这儿 - 他去哪儿了？罗杰呢？
- Roger's not here, - Where is he? Where's Roger?
床下
Under the bed,
罗杰 是爸爸
Roger, It's Papa,
他们走了 他们走了 他们走了
They've gone, They've gone, they've gone,
来 来 快
Come, come, Come on,
噢 亲爱的 好了 甜心 没事儿了
Oh, my darling, It's okay, sweetie, It's okay,
来 没事儿 没事儿了
Come on, it's okay, It's okay,
- 到房顶去 塔莎娜 - 房顶？
- Go to the roof, Tatiana, - The roof?
是的 不错 马上去房顶
Yes, yes, go to the roof right now,
是的 你好 请接比齐蒙戈将军
Yes, good day, General Bizimungu, please,
他去哪儿了？
He is where?
不 这让人无法接受
No, that is unacceptable,
谁下令这样做的？
Who would order such a thing?
是的 你们找到将军了吗？
Yes, did you find the general?
先生们 来喝点酒
Gentlemen, please have some beer,
把房客名单拿给我
Get me the guest list,
是 先生
Yes, sir,
喂？
Yes?
抱歉 先生 我和基加利的保罗通了电话
Sorry, sir, but I have a call from Paul in Kigali.
他说是紧急情况
He says it's urgent.
保罗 你还好吗？
Paul, are you all right?
我们遇到大麻烦了 先生
We have a big problem, sir.
什么麻烦？
What?
胡图族的军队来了
The Hutu army have come,
他们命令我们…所有人…都离开饭店
They've ordered us-- all of us--out of the hotel,
他们为什么这么做？
Why are they doing this?
我向他们会将我们统统杀掉
I think they will kill us all,
杀掉？
Kill?
你的意思是…所有人？有多少人？
What do you mean,,,all? How many?
工作人员100个 还有800多的房客
We have 100 staff and now more than 800 guests,
- 800？！ - 是的 先生
- 800?! - Yes, sir.
800人都是图西族和胡图族难民
There are now 800 Tutsi and Hutu refugees.
我没有时间了 先生
I do not have much time left, sir,
我要感谢你
I want to thank you
为我以及我家人所做的一切
for everything that you have done for me and my family,
并感谢我在比利时航空公司的所有朋友
and please thank all of my friends at Sabena.
保罗 等等
Paul, wait,
我要你先别挂电话 等在电话旁
I'm gonna put you on hold, Stay by the phone,
- 你们的报纸呢？ - 我们没有报纸 先生
- Where are your papers? - We don't have any papers, sir,
我们没有报纸 都在房里烧掉了
We don't have any papers, They got burnt in the house,
路易斯 接通联合国 告诉他们发生的一切
Louis, get on to the U,N, Tell them what's happening,
需要帮忙吗 先生？
Did you need something, sir?
玛丽 给首相办公室打个电话
Mary, call the prime minister's office,
就说我有话要立刻和他说
Tell them I must speak with him now,
好的
Okay,
保罗 在吗？
Paul, are you there?
在 先生
Yes, sir,
谁能制止这一切 我打电话去？
Who can I call to stop this?
法国人 他们给胡图族提供武器的
The French, They supply the Hutu army,
尽一切可能争取时间 我马上给你电话
Do everything you can to buy time, I'll call you right back,
你在干什么 杜比？
What are you doing, Dube?
那个中尉 先生 他要看房客的名单
The lieutenant, sir, he wants to see the guest list.
- 再去给他们拿点啤酒来 - 渴吗 弟兄们？来点啤酒？
- Go and get these boys some more beer. - Thirsty, boy? You like beer?
谢谢
Thank you.
跟我来 拜托
Come with me, please.
先生 这是两周前的
Sir, that was two weeks ago.
给你 先生
Here you are, sir.
安德森 亚瑟斯 布里亚…
Anderson, Arthurs, Boulier...
这是什么？
What is this?
房客名单 先生
It is the guest list, sir.
你想骗我？
Are you trying to make a fool of me?
没有 总统被杀后我们就停止登记姓名了
No. We stopped taking names after the president was murdered.
这是仅有的房客名单 先生
This is the only guest list, sir.
留下的没有一个是欧洲人！
There are no Europeans left!
马上给我这儿所有蟑螂的名单
Get me the names of all the cockroaches in there now.
- 这需要点时间 - 我们没时间了
- That will take time. - We don't have time.
要是我拿不到名单 我就会找出叛徒
If I don't have the names so that I can pick out the traitors,
然后杀了这儿的所有人
then I'll kill everyone in there.
从你开始
Starting with you.
快去
Leave.
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
你给谁打了电话？
Who did you call?
- 我给谁打了电话？ - 别对我撒谎！
- Who did I call? - Don't lie to me!
你叫什么？
What is your name?
卢斯赛伯吉纳
Rusesabagina.
保罗・卢斯赛伯吉纳
Paul Rusesabagina.
我记住你了
I'll remember you.
- 我们走 - 快点 我们走
- Let's go. - Come on, we're leaving.
他们走了
They've gone.
保罗 保罗
Paul. Paul.
我真担心你
I was afraid for you.
先生 比利时航空的主席来电找你
Sir, the president of Sabena is on the phone for you.
我要去和他谈谈
I must talkwith this man.
- 提伦斯先生 - 保罗 情况怎么样？
- Mr. Tillens. - Paul. what's going on?
他们走了 谢谢 先生 你怎么做的？
They left. Thank you, sir. What did you do?
我与法国总统办公室联系过了
I got through to the French president's office.
呃 谢谢你 你挽救了我们
Well, thank you. You have saved our lives.
我再三恳请法国和比利时派兵返回搭救你们
I pleaded with the French and the Belgians to go back and get you all.
但恐怕他们不会这样做
I am afraid this is not going to happen.
他们都是胆小怕事的人 保罗
They're cowards, Paul.
卢旺达不会为他们赢得一张选票
Rwanda is not worth a single vote to any of them.
无论是法国人、英国人、美国人
The French, the British, the Americans.
很抱歉 保罗
I am sorry, Paul.
谢谢
Thank you.
不会有人来救援我们……
There will be no rescue...
…来干涉我们的事儿了
...no intervention for us.
我们只能靠自己
We can only save ourselves.
你们很多人都认识些海外的有权势的人
Many of you know influential people abroad.
你们要和这些人联系
You must call these people.
拜托 把这些传真到这个号码 谢谢
Please, fax this to this number. Thank you.
你们要告诉他们我们的遭遇
You must tell them what will happen to us.
和他们说再见
Say good-bye.
但当你们说再见时
But when you say good-bye,
就好像通过电话你们能抓住他们的手一样
say it as though you are reaching through the phone and holding their hand.
让他们知道 如果他们放手…
Let them know that if they let go of that hand...
…你们就会死亡
...you will die.
我们要让他们感到惭愧 以至于来帮助我们
We must shame them into sending help.
最重要的是 这不是一个难民营
Most importantly, this cannot be a refugee camp.
部族民兵认为米勒・科林斯饭店是一家四星级的比利时饭店
The lnterhamwe believe that the Mille Collines is a four-star Sabena hotel.
这是唯一能让我们生存的方式
That is the only thing that is keeping us alive.
账单打印好了吗？
Have you printed the bills?
谢谢 拜托清除记录
Thank you. Now please erase the register.
- 清除？ - 是的 我不希望看到有姓名出现
- Erase it? - Yes. I want no names to appear there.
老板 木匠准备就绪
Boss, the carpenters are ready.
让他们去掉所有房间门上的号码
Tell them to remove all of the numbers from the doors.
- 加上什么？ - 什么都别加
- And put what? - And put nothing.
你好 这是最后一个礼拜的账单
Good day. Here is your bill for the last week.
如果你无法支付或不能支付
If you cannot pay or think you will not be able to pay,
请到餐厅去 杜比会帮你处理 谢谢
please go to the banquet room and Dube will take care of you. Thank you.
国务院认为是否…
Does the State Department have a view
会发生种族屠杀呢？
as to whether or not what is happening could be genocide?
我们有足够的证据表明种族屠杀行动已经发生
We have every reason to believe that acts of genocide have occurred.
为了进行种族屠杀 采取了多少次行动？
How many acts of genocide does it take to make genocide?
艾伦 这个问题我无法回答
Alan. that's just not a question that I'm in a position to answer.
很明显 你没有孤立地使用…
Is it true that you have specific guidance
“种族屠杀”这个说法 而总是使用…
not to use the word "genocide" in isolation.
“**行动”的说法 是这样的吗？
but always to preface it with this word "acts of"?
我尽可能使用我觉得最好的说法
I have guidance which I try to use as best as I can.
我…
I have--
我们在使用时要做到标准化
There are formulations that we are using
以便我们保持一致性…
that we are trying to be consistent in our use of--
抱歉这不是格兰奥兰治牌的酒
I'm sorry it is not Glenmorangie.
只要是苏格兰威士忌就行
As long as it is scotch.
你的白人朋友抛弃了你
Your white friends have abandoned you.
- 看上去是如此 - 呃 别担心
- So it would seem. - Well, don't worry.
- 我会照顾你的 - 你这么说我很高兴
- I will take care of you. - I'm glad to hear that
因为我不知道 或许你愿意派几个警察
because I was wondering if perhaps you could spare us a few policemen.
来保护我们 先生
To protect us, sir.
- 警察都很忙 保罗 - 是的 我知道
- The police are very busy, Paul. - Yes, I'm aware of this.
但我上次和比利时航空的主席提及时
But when I last spoke to the president of Sabena,
他向我保证 无论谁帮助保护了比利时的财产
he assured me that anyone who helped protect Belgian property
都会得到很好的回报的
would be well rewarded.
我看看我能不能帮忙
I will see what I can do.
抱歉离开一下 先生
Excuse me momentarily, sir.
我们所有的啤酒哪儿去了？
Where has all our beer gone?
先生 格莱戈瓦拿走了啤酒
Sir, Gregoire has been taking beer.
多少？
How much beer?
很多
Many.
…下来参加招待会 然后他对我说
...come down to the reception. And then he says to me,
“想要姑娘吗？”
"How do you want the girls?"
那是我们的蟑螂经理 喜欢亲别人屁股
There's our cockroach manager. Always kissing ass.
将军…
General...
很高兴你能来
I'm glad you came by.
我无意中听到一些传言 我想你应该知道
I overheard something that I think you should know about.
你听到什么？
What did you overhear?
联合国上校和美国使馆官员的讨论
It was a discussion between a U.N. Colonel and an American Embassy official.
他们说什么？
And what did they say?
美国人向上校保证 他们会关注一切的
The American assured the colonel that they would watch everything.
怎么关注？他们都打道回府了 保罗
How? They have gone, Paul.
利用间谍、卫星
With their spies. Satellites.
美国人啊
Americans.
噢 格莱戈瓦！
Oh, Gregoire!
知道吗 我很钦佩你 将军
You know, I admire you, General.
你是如何管住这些疯狂的士兵的？
How do you keep command of your men amid such madness?
- 我是个强人 保罗 - 希望我也能像你一样
- I am a strong man, Paul. - I wish I were more like you.
- 我是说 看看我的雇员 - 干杯
- I mean, look at my staff. - Cheers.
他们都不工作了 谁也不听
He won't work, listens to no one.
- 他是雇员吗？ - 噢 是的
- He is staff? - Oh, yes.
是的
Yes.
回去工作 你这个懒人！快去！
Get back to work, you slug! Go!
卫星？
Satellites?
我还想说 美国人就藏在树林里呢
What was I going to say, that the Americans were hiding in the trees?
- 有什么不妥？ - 我得出去找点吃的回来
- What's the matter? - I have to go out and get food.
- 出去？去哪儿？ - 去乔治・卢塔甘达那儿
- Go out? Where? - To George Rutaganda's place.
不 不 不
No. No, no.
我必须去 塔莎娜
I have to, Tatiana.
只有给他钱的时候 我们才有点价值
We are only as valuable as the money we give to him.
你不能单独去
You cannot go alone.
我不会一个人去 我会带上格莱戈瓦
I'm not going alone. I'll take Gregoire with me.
他是胡图族人 现在他又想在我面前挣表现
He's a good Hutu, and he wants to impress me now.
很高兴你还在工作 格莱戈瓦
It is good to see you back at work, Gregoire.
- 拜托 先生 请接受我得道歉 - 拜托 拜托
- Please, sir, accept my humblest apologies. - Please, please.
早上我们有个工作
We have a job this morning.
我们要去看看乔治・卢塔甘达
We are going to see George Rutaganda.
去把车开过来
Please get the van.
给我看看你的身份证
Show me your l.D.
还记得图西族妇女习惯于…
Remember how those Tutsi women used to look down
低下她们的长鼻梁看胡图族人吗？
their long noses at Hutu men?
现在她们要为他们的生命而祈祷
Now they beg for their lives.
我来这儿看我的朋友乔治・卢塔甘达
I'm here to see my friend George Rutaganda.
在图西族下流女人死之前 建议大家先去尝尝她们的味道
I say taste those Tutsi whores before they die.
这样她们才知道到底什么是胡图族政权 我的勇士们
Then they'll know what Hutu power is. my warriors.
记住 每一只蟑螂都会发动奇袭
Remember. one cockroach can start an infestation.
我们要彻底铲除这些害虫
We need to exterminate these vermin.
嘿 保罗 我的老朋友
Hey, Paul, my old friend.
是图西族妓女 找我有什么事儿？
Tutsi prostitutes and witches. So, what can I do for you?
- 我需要点补给品 乔治 - 随时都可以
- I need supplies, George. - Anytime.
保罗 所有的东西价格都翻倍了 知道吗？
Paul, everything is double the price now. You understand that?
知道 我需要大米、豆荚
Yes. I need rice, beans,
奶粉、啤酒 还有你最好的威士忌
powdered milk, beer, and your best whiskey.
啤酒有 但威士忌没有
Beer yes, but whiskey no.
没有威士忌？
You have no whiskey?
没有威士忌 烈酒都没有了
No whiskey, no spirits.
你那些…富有的房客们只能忍受一下了
Your...rich guests will have to do without their scotch.
总之 保罗 我已经让那些牛流够了血
Anyway, Paul, I have bled that cow enough now.
你在说什么 乔治？
What are you saying, George?
你饭店里的那些富有的蟑螂
Your rich cockroaches at the hotel,
他们拿着钱没有用的
their money is no good to them anymore.
很快所有的图西族人都得死
Soon all the Tutsis will be dead.
你难道没有想过 你不可能将他们杀绝的？
You do not honestly believe that you can kill them all?
为什么不能？
And why not?
Why not?
我们已经杀掉一半了
We are halfway there already.
保罗 你要12袋大米？
So, Paul, you want 12 bags of rice?
给他12袋大米和4箱啤酒
Give him 12 bags of rice and 4 crates of beer.
好的 先生 马上
Yes, sir, right away.
噢 还有 保罗 我免费给你一箱饮料 拿给孩子们喝
Oh, and, Paul, I'll give you a crate of soft drinks for the kids free of charge.
好的
Yes.
十袋豆荚 来 快点
Ten bags of beans. Come, quick.
都装上车 你
And put those in the van. You.
我要提醒一下你 朋友
Let me give you a little tip, my friend.
我们军队将军说 “别靠近米勒・科林斯饭店
Our generals in army say, "Don't go near the Mille Collines
否则他们会派比利时士兵来这儿”
or they will send the Belgian soldiers back here."
很快这些将军会离开 由我们负责
But soon those generals will have gone and we will be in charge.
到时候就开始屠宰你的肥牛了
It's time to butcher that fat cow of yours for the meat.
我们走
Let's go.
或许你可以帮我 保罗
Maybe you could help us, Paul.
你旅馆里有很重要的叛徒
You have some very important traitors at that hotel.
如果我们去把他们抓来
Now, if we were to get them,
或许我们会让你留下一两只蟑螂在你身边
then maybe we would let you have one or two cockroaches of your own.
明白吗？
Do you understand?
天快亮了 乔治
It is almost dawn, George.
我们真的要走了
We really must be going.
回去时走河边 比较安全
Take the river road back. It's clear.
- 格莱戈瓦 - 怎么了？
- Gregoire. - What is going on now?
- 你开出路了 - 不 我在路上
- You've driven off the road. - No, I'm on the road.
你要让我们都掉河里去？停车 停车
You're going to put us in the river. Stop the car, stop the car.
倒车 格莱戈瓦
Back up the car, Gregoire.
听我说
Listen to me.
今天看到的对谁都别讲
You will tell no one what you have seen here today.
谁都别讲 格莱戈瓦
No one, Gregoire.
杜比 去帮格莱戈瓦卸货 谢谢
Dube. Please help Gregoire to unload the van. Thank you.
噢 亲爱的
Oh, dear.
噢 上帝！
Oh, God!
- 先生 - 杜比！
- Sir. - Dube!
- 先生 你没事儿吧？ - 别进来 别进来
- Sir, are you okay? - Don't come in. Don't come in.
我马上出来
I'll be out in a minute.
- 先生 你没事儿吧？ - 是的 我没事儿 杜比
- Sir, are you okay? - Yes, I'm all right, Dube.
别进来 我就出来
Don't come in. I'll be out.
成百上千
Hundreds.
不计其数
It was too many to count.
为什么这些人这么残忍？
Why are people so cruel?
憎恨
Hatred.
疯了 不知道
Insanity. I don't know.
拿去
There you go.
她把手指伸进汤里了？
Is she putting her fingers in the soup?
噢 是的
Oh, yes.
…和你 和你无关
...to do with you. Nothing to do with me.
我记得…
I remember...
不 不 不 你错了
No, no, no, you make a mistake.
- 嗨 - 跟我来
- Hello. - Come with me.
- 我们去哪儿？ - 来
- Where are we going? - Just come.
很美
It's beautiful.
喜欢吗？
You like it?
听说我们得偿还这一切
I hear we must pay for everything.
是的 不错
Yes, this is true.
那…这个值多少？
So...how much for this?
一个吻
A kiss.
你是个好人 保罗・卢斯赛伯吉纳
You are a good man, Paul Rusesabagina.
我像你坦白一件事
I have a confession.
当你还是个护士的时候…
When you worked as the nurse...
- 在鲁亨盖里？ - 是的
- In Ruhengeri? - Yes.
我们第一次见面…
When we first met...
是我让你调到了基加里
I had you transferred to Kigali.
什么？
What?
我贿赂了卫生部长 把你调到了基加里
I bribed the Minister of Health to have you transferred to Kigali.
- 为什么？ - 这样我们更近些
- Why? - To be closer.
这样我才能娶你
So that I could marry you.
你贿赂了什么？
What was the bribe?
- 我对你来说值多少？ - 很多
- What am I worth to you? - It was substantial.
- 告诉我是什么 - 一辆车
- Tell me what it was. - A car.
- 什么车？ - 这有关系吗？
- What sort of car? - What does that matter?
我想知道
I want to know.
大众
A Volkswagen.
希望是一辆新的
I hope it was a new one.
我的一生是幸福的 你和我 是的
We have had a good life, you and l. Yes.
感谢上帝 我们共同度过的每一天
I thank God every day for the time we've had.
- 我们必须得有个计划 - 计划？
- We have to have a plan. - A plan?
孩子们不能看着我们先死去
Our children cannot see us die first.
要使民兵来了 你尽快到这上面来
If the militia come, you must come up here as quick as you can.
- 拜托 我不想… - 你必须上来 塔莎娜
- Please, I don't want to-- - You must come up here, Tatiana.
- 我不想听你这样说 拜托 - 我们必须得说 塔莎娜
- I don't want you to talk like this, please. - We have to, Tatiana.
如果我没有挺过来
If I do not make it,
你一定要牵着孩子们的手…
you must take all of our children by the hand...
…你一定要跳
...and you must jump.
- 你在说什么？我不会… - 你必须如此 塔莎娜
- What are you saying? I could never-- - You have to, Tatiana.
- 你向我保证 - 你在说什么？
- You have to promise me. - What are you saying?
塔莎娜 不要死在弯刀下
Tatiana, the machete is no way to die.
你得向我保证你会那样做
You have to promise me you will do it.
我不…
I cannot do--
你必须向我保证 塔莎娜 拜托
You have to promise me, Tatiana. Please.
向我保证你会那样做
Promise me you will do it.
拜托 塔莎娜
Please, Tatiana.
好
Yes.
抱歉 我爱你
I'm sorry. I love you.
我爱你
I love you.
我要抓住你！
I'm gonna get you!
黛安 伊利 你最好知道
Diane, Elys, you know better.
谁都不能到饭店前面来 我给你说过
No one can be at the front of the hotel. I have told you this.
- 带孩子们去后面 快 - 抱歉 爸爸
- Take these children in the back. Hurry. - Sorry, Papa.
- 来 孩子们 来 - 谢谢 杜比
- Come, children. Come. - Thank you, Dube.
保罗 我有好消息了
Paul, I've got good news.
祝贺你们 你们的电话起作用了
Congratulations. Your calls have worked.
我拿到了这些家庭的出境签证
I have exit visas for the following families.
阿布克苏 坦桑尼亚
Abukesu, Tanzania.
比多利 肯尼亚
Bidori, Kenya.
基图朗伽 赞比亚
Gituaranga, Zambia.
哈利路亚！（赞美上帝）
Hallelujah!
喀里萨 比利时
Khalesa, Belgium.
噢 谢谢！
Oh, thank you!
达库兹…
Dakuzi...
肯尼亚
Kenya.
纳桑波 赞比亚
Masambo, Zambia.
辛咕噜 加纳
Zinguru, Ghana.
卢斯赛伯吉纳 比利时
Rusesabagina, Belgium.
好了 就这些
All right, that's it.
记住 这些家庭早上7点前做好准备
So remember, families be ready at 7 a.m.
我们走
Let's go.
- 上校？ - 什么
- Colonel? - Yeah.
奥德特和吉恩・巴提斯一定在名单上
Now, certainly Odette and Jean Baptiste are on the list.
抱歉 吉恩 奥德特
I'm sorry, Jean, Odette.
但我保证不久又会有另一班飞机的
But I have been assured there will be another plane soon.
抱歉
Excuse me.
别担心 塔莎 下一批会有的
Don't worry, Tatsi, we'll make it to the next list.
是的
Yeah.
女孩…保罗 我不会留下她们而去
The girls-- Paul, I will not leave without them.
你带了些什么来？
What have you brought us?
抗生素、药物补给、一般急救用品
Antibiotics, medical supplies, general first aid.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 听说有航班来接了 - 是的
- I hear there's to be a convoy. - Yes.
名单上有你吗？
Are you on the list?
阿彻夫人 我有个难以接受的请求
Madame Archer, I have an impossible request of you.
你有办法去那位老太太那儿
Is there any way that you could return to the old woman
把我的侄女带过来吗？
and bring the girls back here to us?
保罗 半个城市在战斗中都被摧毁了
Paul, that side of town has been destroyed in the fighting.
他们很可能已经死了
They're probably dead.
阿彻夫人 我求求你了 她们现在无亲无故
Madame Archer, I'm begging you. Those girls have no one now.
我尽力而为
I'll try.
我早上7就要离开了
We have to leave by 7 a.m.
你走了谁来照顾孤儿们？
Who'll take care of the orphans when you're gone?
奥德特 奥德特会照料他们 直到我们带他们离开这儿
Odette. Odette will care for them until we can get them out of here.
保罗 你说说 哪个国家会接受这20名卢旺达孤儿？
Tell me, Paul, what country's gonna take 20 Rwandan orphans?
我会找到人的 我向你保证
I will find someone. I promise you.
- 谢谢 - 谢谢
- Thanks. - Thank you.
来 牵着我手
Come on, take my hand.
非洲新闻播报 今天红十字代表声称
News Service Africa. Today a Red Cross representative
卢旺达种族冲突的死亡路进一步攀升
claimed that the death rate in the Rwandan conflict
死亡人数达500,000
may have climbed to as many as 500.000 victims.
一个报道称有40,000具
One report stated that 40.000 bodies
尸体被遗弃在维多利亚湖
had been removed from Lake Victoria.
她在哪儿？
Where is she?
不知道 我们等到七点
I don't know. We wait until seven.
如果到时候他没有带回姑娘们…
If she is not back with the girls by then...
…她就可能不会来了
...she may not be coming.
谢谢
Thank you.
拜托 带着这些邮件
Please, take these letters.
好的 我会带着的
Yes, I will take your letters.
太感谢你了 保罗 带着这些邮件
Thank you so much, Paul, taking the letter.
- 非常感谢 - 是的 抱歉
- Thank you so much. - Yes, I am sorry.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
抱歉 希望我能帮你们更多 抱歉
I am sorry. I wish I could have done more. I am sorry.
上帝与你同在
God be with you.
- 是的 你有孩子吗？ - 是的 你可以走了
- Yes, do you have any children? - Yes, you're clear to go.
不 抱歉 没用的
No, sorry, no good.
来 来 孩子们
Come. Come, children.
塔莎 来
Tatsi, come.
拜托 保罗 姑娘们 我们在等一下吧
Please, Paul, the girls. We wait a little longer.
我们不能等了 不能等了 塔莎
We cannot wait. We cannot wait, Tatsi.
来吧
There you go.
出发！
Let's move out!
好运 先生
Good luck, sir.
我不能走 你拉着塔莎娜 照顾我的家人
I am not leaving. You hold Tatiana. Take care of my family.
保罗 保罗！
Paul. Paul!
我不能眼睁睁看着这些人去死 我不能留下这些人不管
I cannot leave these people to die. I cannot leave these people.
爸爸！
Papa!
罗杰！罗杰 我会乘下一班飞机的
Roger! Roger, I will follow on the next flight.
不 别扔下我！保罗！
No, don't leave me! Paul!
别担心 别担心 孩子们 你爸爸没事儿的
Don't worry. Don't worry, children. Your father's going to be okay.
爸爸！
Papa!
- 别担心 他没事儿的 - 我要爸爸！
- Don't worry. He's okay. - I want Papa!
没事儿的
It's okay.
我觉得那些庇护蟑螂的胡图族人
I say those Hutus who shelter the cockroaches
同蟑螂毫无差别
are the same as cockroaches.
- 他们是同类 - 太疯狂了
- They are all the same. - This is crazy.
他们应该有相同的命运 这里是RTLM（千丘广播电台）
Their fate should be the same. This is RTLM.
图西族叛军一定对征兵表示否认
The Tutsi cockroaches of the rebel army must be denied recruits.
来吧 胡图族人 坟墓尚有余位
Come on. good Hutus. The graves are not yet full.
- 谁愿意去填补空缺？ - 该死的电台
- Who will help us fill them? - That goddamn radio station.
好 是的 他们正去机场
Okay. Yeah, they are going to the airport.
锁定你的广播频率 我听到些紧急新闻
Stand by your radios. I am hearing some urgent news.
- 老板！拜托 快来！ - 现在不行 杜比
- Boss! Please, come quick! - Not now, Dube.
很重要！正在广播 你快来听
It is important! It is on the radio. You have to hear it.
我们收到非常重要消息 说有蟑螂
We have received reports of very important cockroaches
和叛徒试图逃离米勒・科林斯饭店
and traitors trying to escape from the Mille Collines Hotel.
收起你们的武器吧
Gather up your weapons.
锁定您的广播频率 我们会有后续报道
Stand by your radios. We will keep you informed.
他们正被偷运出国…
They are being smuggled away...
不 不！谁告诉他们的 杜比？
No, no! Who told them of this, Dube?
我看到格莱戈瓦了 先生
I saw Gregoire, sir. It is Gregoire.
一定是格莱戈瓦 我在大巴上看到了他
I saw him leaving in our bus.
拜托 先生 你要什么我都给你
Please, sir, I will give you whatever I have.
我要知道谁离开了饭店 而不是其他人
I say who leaves that hotel, and no one else.
比齐蒙戈将军 他们遭到了伏击
General Bizimungu, they are driving into an ambush.
慢点
Slow down.
别慌
Stay calm.
- 怎么回事？ - 车停了
- What is happening? - We're stopping.
你们车上藏了蟑螂
You have got cockroaches in these trucks.
没有 不是 车上都是联合国的人员
No, no. I've got U.N. personnel in these trucks.
我获准可以通过路障
I've got permission to go through these roadblocks.
我要搜查车厢
I'm going to search these trucks.
你不能搜查这个车队
You are not going to search this convoy.
- 我要 - 掩护我
- I am. - Cover me.
到后面去
Go to the back.
别靠近车辆 别靠近车辆！马上离开！
Get away from that truck. Get away from that truck! Now!
退后！你们不能伤及这些人
Get back! You're not to hurt these people.
退后！退后！
Get back! Move back!
听着 我给你讲 你车上藏有蟑螂
Look, I told you, you've got cockroaches in your truck.
不 不 不 他们是联合国批准的政治难民
No, no, no. They're political refugees under U.N. sanction.
有消息称 我们自己的军中有胆小怕事之人
News has come to us that we have cowards in our own army
不让我们惩罚他们
who will not let us punish them.
不！
No!
你想从米勒・科林斯饭店带走蟑螂？
You're moving cockroaches from Mille Collines?
不 先生 不 先生 他们是政治难民
No, sir. No, sir, they're political refugees.
- 他们不能离开米勒・科林斯饭店 - 他们都不能离开
- They cannot leave Mille Collines. - They are not leaving.
阻止他！
Stop him!
你个混蛋！
You bastard!
你叫什么？
What's your name?
- 你叫什么名字？ - 我不知道…
- What's your name? - I can't think...
- 杀了他们！ - 所有人都离开这儿！走！
- Kill them! - Get everybody out of here! Move it!
你叫什么名字？叫什么名字？
What's your name? What's your name?
我们走！快开车！
Let's move! Drive!
走！出去！
Move! Get out!
出去 我开枪了！
Out, or I'll shoot!
出去！
Get out!
开车 开车！我们走！
Drive, drive! Let's go!
帮我们离开这儿
Help us get out of here.
清理路面！
Clear the street!
我又收到了消息 胡图族人
I am receiving more news. good Hutus.
我在车上发现了
I have learned that the traitor Rusesabagina's cockroaches
叛徒卢斯赛伯吉纳曾庇护的蟑螂
are on a truck.
他们的头值10,000法郎！
10.000 francs for their heads!
别动 给我你的衣服 快
Stay still. Give me your shirt, quickly.
快来 保罗 快来 快来！
Come on, Paul. Come on, come on!
快来 这儿 这儿 手给我 来
Come on, here, here. Give me your hand. Come on.
拜托 拜托
Please, please.
- 嘿 医生 叫个医生来！ - 你快点 拜托
- Hey, medic. Get a medic over here! - You need to hurry up, please.
来 快 快
Come, hurry, hurry.
- 我来帮你 - 来个人帮帮这个警卫好吗
- Let me help you. - Someone give this guard a hand, please.
噢 塔莎娜 我亲爱的
Oh, Tatiana, my darling.
- 我好担心你 - 别让车挡在路上！
- I was so worried about you. - Move that truck out of the way!
带他进去！
Get him inside!
塔莎娜 塔莎娜
Tatiana. Tatiana.
你扔下我不管 你扔下我不管
You left me. You left me.
这个拿回去 我不想要 我不想要
Take this. I don't want it. I don't want it.
你说你不会撇下我的 而你却扔下了我 你这个骗子！
You said you'd never leave me, and you left me. You are a liar!
抱歉 抱歉
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
- 很抱歉 - 爸爸 爸爸
- I'm sorry. - Papa, Papa.
- 爸爸 妈妈！ - 我爱你们
- Papa, Mama! - I love you.
我想让你们安全 你们所有人
I wanted you to be safe, all of you.
决定不是由你一个人说了算
That was not your decision to make.
我们应该一起决定 我们发过誓的
We make our decisions together. That was our promise.
你说得对
You're right.
当车开走的一瞬间 我理解
I knew that the minute the truck pulled away.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
来 再多点水
Come on, put some more water.
他们在干什么？
What are they doing?
杜比
Dube.
抱歉 先生 水阀被关了 我们只能用这个了
I'm sorry, sir. They shut down the water. This is all we have.
将军
General.
我的补给品呢？
Where are my supplies?
抱歉 先生 仓库都空了
I'm sorry, sir. The cellar is empty.
你一无所有 还打电话给我 求我帮你？
You have nothing, and yet you call me, begging me for help?
你知道为了保护这些蟑螂 我惹了多大麻烦？
Do you know the trouble I have protecting these cockroaches?
先生 我有房客们的钱
Sir, I have money from the guests.
卢旺达法郎！
Rwandan francs!
这些你只能拿去擦屁股
Those are only good for wiping your ass.
我不会再帮你了 保罗
There is nothing more I can do for you, Paul.
不会再给你警察 不会再给你保护
No more police, no more protection.
让联合国保护你吧
Let the U.N. take care of you.
开车 走！
Drive. Go!
对此比利时航空有什么措施？
What would Sabena make of this?
当心！
Watch out!
趴下 趴下！
Get down, get down!
受伤了吗？到外面去
Are you hurt? Go outside.
带着别动 这儿有碎玻璃 我来解决
Please stay still. There's glass here. I will get it out.
有人受伤吗 奥德特？
Is anyone hurt, Odette?
很多人被割伤、擦伤
Lots of cuts and bruises.
感谢上帝这只是储藏室
Thank God it was a storeroom.
在卢旺达 人道主义机构报道称
And in Rwanda. humanitarian agencies report
图西族叛军的快速增长
that a rapid advance by the Tutsi rebel army
让大批胡图族难民逃向刚果
has sparked a mass evacuation of Hutu refugees towards the Congo.
一名援助者描述说
One aid worker described it
这是近代史上最大的一次难民潮
as the largest refugee exodus in modern history.
反叛分子占领了半个城市
The rebels have taken half the city,
他们提出的条件 胡图族将军愿意接受
and they have proposed a deal the Hutu generals are willing to accept.
反叛分子决定用胡图族的囚犯作交换
The rebels will exchange their Hutu prisoners,
你们呢 所有的人
and you people, all of you,
将被转移到叛军后方的安全地带
will be able to move behind the rebel lines where it's safe.
部族民兵呢 他们怎么样？
The lnterhamwe, what about them?
- 没人能控制他们 - 他们现在要杀了我们所有人
- No one controls them. - This time they will kill us all.
如果呆在这儿 他们才会杀了我们所有人
They will kill us all if we stay here.
我们必须把握机会
We have to take the chance.
我们应该什么时候撤离？
What time should we be ready to leave?
我想两天后应该可以 保罗
I can put it together in two days, Paul.
两天？
Two days?
上校 我们不能在这儿呆上两天的时间
Colonel, there is no way that we can hold out for two days.
我一无所有了 无法贿赂他们
I have nothing left to bribe them with.
上校 两天后我们都会死的
Colonel, we will all be dead in two days.
黛安…让你妈妈睡吧
Diane...Iet your mother rest.
你也睡了 甜心 睡吧
You rest too, sweetheart. Go to sleep.
外交官饭店
Diplomat.
什么？
What?
我要去外交官饭店
I have to go to the Diplomat.
- 你要干什么？ - 我们得去外交官饭店
- What are you doing? - We have to go to the Diplomat.
- 去干什么？ - 你的东西 放在那儿
- To do what? - Your items, they are there.
让你的警察守住门好吗 先生？
Will you please put your policemen at the gate, sir?
不 我们先去看看你有什么给我
No. Let us see what you have to offer first.
噢 不 阿彻夫人
Oh, no. Madame Archer.
快走 快走！
Move, move!
- 掩护我们 - 是的 先生
- Cover us. - Yes, sir.
快！
Hurry!
快点 让我看
Come on, show me.
看这个 不错 对吧？
Look at this. Nice, yes?
还有这些
And here you are.
反叛分子越来越近了 对吗？
The rebels are getting closer, yes?
反叛分子能将此变为坟场
The rebels can have this graveyard.
我们下令所有人都离开这个城市
We have ordered everyone out of the city.
来
Here.
喝一口
Have a drink.
你知道苏格兰人怎么叫这个？
You know what the Scottish call it?
不知道
No.
Uisge beatha――生命之泉
Uisge beatha--water of life.
我去世界上最好的单一麦芽酿酒厂参观过
I went once on a tour of the finest single malt distillery in the world.
- 你去过苏格兰吗？ - 没有 先生
- Have you ever been to Scotland? - No, sir.
很不错的国家
Wonderful country.
能玩很棒的高尔夫球
Wonderful golf.
我不知道 我是否还能回去？
I wonder, will I ever go back?
你觉得呢？
What do you think?
不
No.
我希望我们都能接触到许许多多的东西 将军
I hope we all get to do a great many things, General.
请问我们可以走了吗 先生？
Can we go now, please, sir?
我要帮你个大忙 保罗
I am going to do you a great favor, Paul.
- 士兵 - 是 先生！
- Private. - Yes, sir!
小心装好 放在我吉普车上 守好
Pack those carefully, put them in my jeep, and guard them.
我要带你到吉塔拉马我们新司令部去
I am going to take you with us to our new headquarters in Gitarama.
我不想去吉塔拉马 先生
I do not want to go to Gitarama, sir.
呃 你不能回饭馆去
Well, you can't go back to the hotel.
疯狂的人正奔向那儿
The crazy men are on their way there now.
先生…将军 我们得回去 我要带走我的家人
Sir...General, we must go back so that I can get my family.
相信我 比在这儿境况好得多
Trust me, we are better off here.
将军 这是困难时期
General, these are difficult times.
我们需要相互帮助
We need to help one another.
我需要你帮我什么 保罗？
And what help can I get from you, Paul?
- 你是众人瞩目的人 先生 - 那又怎样？
- You are a marked man, sir. - How so?
你在名单上
You are on a list.
美国人把你写在战犯的名单上
The Americans have you on their list as a war criminal.
保罗 我很讨厌也很厌倦你骗我
Paul, I am sick and tired of your lies.
你傻了吗 将军？
Are you stupid, General?
你觉得那些人会怎么做？
How do you think these people operate?
在这儿你胸前有五颗勋章
You sit here with five stars on your chest.
你想想是谁让你得到的？
Who do you think they are coming after?
很好
Fine.
我们去吉塔拉马 你就会一直写在那个名单上
We will go to Gitarama, and you will stay on that list.
- 我没有从事任何战争犯罪 - 谁来评判呢？
- I committed no war crimes. - Who will tell them?
你要我来说 你是如何帮助饭店的人的
You need me to tell them how you helped at the hotel.
他们谴责你带来的不幸 他们说你领导了屠杀
They blame you for all their misfortunes. They say you led the massacres.
我没有领导屠杀！
I led no massacres!
你觉得他们会信你吗？
Do you think they're going to believe you?
你去告诉他们真相！
You will tell them the truth!
我绝不告诉他们 除非你帮我
I will tell them nothing unless you help me.
你要干什么 杀了我？
What are you going to do, shoot me?
杀了我啊
Shoot me.
拜托杀了我 上帝赐予我的
Please shoot me. It would be a blessing.
你杀了我的家人我会偿还的
I will pay you to shoot my family.
你不能伤害我
You cannot hurt me.
你去告诉他们 我什么都没干！
You will tell them that I did nothing!
我们走 就现在
We are leaving. Right now.
出来！
Get out!
别让人到门口去！
Get these people away from the gate!
停！停！
Stop it! Stop it!
离开饭店
Clear the hotel.
- 塔莎娜！ - 离开这儿！
- Tatiana! - Get out of here!
- 出去！ - 塔莎娜！
- Get out! - Tatiana!
出去！
Get out!
所有民兵都离开！出去！
All of the militia must leave now! Get out!
噢 不 不！
Oh, no, no!
闭嘴 蟑螂！蹲下！
Shut up, cockroach! Get down!
就是他 就是他！
That's him. That's him!
- 见鬼 - 经理在那儿！
- Shit. - That's the manager!
- 抓住他 抓住他！ - 我看到他了！我看到他了！
- Stop him. Stop him! - I got him! I got him!
呆着别动！
Stay where you are!
塔莎娜！
Tatiana!
- 看到塔莎娜了吗？ - 没有 没看到塔莎娜
- Have you seen Tatiana? - No, I've not seen Tatiana.
- 保罗 怎么了？ - 我要去找我妻子！
- Paul, what is happening? - I have to find my wife!
塔莎娜！
Tatiana!
他们走了 他们走了
They've gone. They've gone.
他们走了
They've gone.
你拿这个干什么？
What were you going to do with this?
我还以为你…
I thought you had...
我还以为你跳了
I thought you had jumped.
所有人都到车上去 拜托
Everyone on the trucks, please.
带上你们的行李 一家人呆在一起
Take your luggage. Families please stay together.
- 噢 拜托 - 大家尽快 拜托
- Oh, please. - As fast as you can, everyone. Please.
所有人都能上去
There's enough room for everyone.
希望有朝一日我们能再回来
I hope someday we will come back.
我们走
Let's move out.
她怎么了？
What is wrong with her?
她发了高烧
She has a very high fever.
我们要去哪儿 爸爸？
Where are we going, Daddy?
安全的地方
Someplace safe.
上帝
My God.
怎么了？
What's happening?
来 我们走 孩子们蹲下来 带孩子们走这边
Come on, let's go. Children on the ground. Bring the children this way.
让他们到后面去 让他们到后面去
Pass them back, pass them back.
别停 别停！直接开过去
Do not stop. Do not stop! Go right on through.
趴下！
Get down!
蹲下！
Stay down!
怎么了？
What's happening there?
是反叛分子 我们正通过前线
It's the rebels. We're crossing the front line.
没事儿了 我们安全了
It's okay. We're safe.
没事儿了
It's okay.
没事儿了 这儿安全了 安全了
It's okay, you are safe here. You are safe.
现在没事儿了 坐下来
It's okay now. Sit back down.
嗨
Hello.
多弄点水来
Get some more water.
医生说他严重脱水
The doctor says he is very dehydrated.
我们到了 来 下来吧
We made it. Come on, let's get down.
- 来 - 没事儿了
- Come on. - It is okay.
- 她病了 - 好的
- She is sick. - Okay.
是的 她病得很厉害 抱住她
Yeah, she's very sick. Take her.
保罗 车在营地的另一边
Paul, the buses are on the other side of camp.
他们要带我去坦桑尼亚
They'll take you to Tanzania.
那就去 保罗 因为我也不知道何时才会再有机会
Go now, Paul, 'cause I don't know when there'd be another opportunity.
- 谢谢 - 是的
- Thank you. - Yeah.
- 好运 - 谢谢
- Good luck. - Thank you.
- 感谢上帝 - 我们到了
- Thank God. - We made it.
拜托 拜托 都到了 对吧？
Please, please. We are here, yeah?
- 谢谢 保罗 - 我们成功了
- Thank you, Paul. - We have made it.
- 谢谢 - 是的 是的 来
- Thank you. - Yes, yes. Come.
经理先生
Mr. Manager.
- 我只是想谢谢你 - 当然 史蒂文
- I just want to thank you. - Of course, Steven.
康斯坦茨！
Constance!
感谢上帝你还活着！见到你真是太高兴了
Thank God you are alive! It's so good to see you.
你见过我哥哥和嫂子吗？
Have you seen my brother and his wife?
都没有
None of them.
有人见过这些人吗？你不认…
Has anyone seen these people? You don't recog--
妈妈 快来看
Mama, come see quick.
- 抱歉 抱歉 - 你在哪儿看到她们的？
- Excuse me, excuse me. - Can you see them anywhere?
这儿 妈妈 看
Here, Mama, look.
拜托
Please.
看到了吗 妈妈？是她们吗？
Do you see them, Mama? Is that them?
是她们吗 妈妈？
Is that them, Mama?
你们认识这些人吗？
Do you recognize these people?
这个小姑娘 她叫爱耐丝 这是卡琳
This little girl, she's Anais, and this is Carine.
认识吗？
Do you recognize them?
- 女士 见过这些姑娘吗？ - 不 没有 没见过
- Ma'am, have you seen these girls? - No, no, I haven't.
有人见过这些姑娘吗？
Have any of you seen these girls?
爱耐丝 那是我哥哥
Anais. And that's my brother.
所有人都上车！
Everybody on the buses!
这儿有感觉吗？
Can you feel anything when I touch here?
所有人都上车！
Everybody on the buses!
别挡在路上好吗？我们过不去了！
Can you move out of the way? We need some room here!
- 我们会发现姑娘们的 塔莎 会的 - 好的
- We'll find the girls, Tatsi. We will. - Okay.
布西？
Boussey?
真的是你
It's you.
哪儿找到这个孩子的？
Where'd you find this child?
刚从米勒・科林斯饭店来的车上下来的
They just arrived on trucks from the Mille Collines.
米勒・科林斯饭店的难民请上车了
All Mille Collines evacuees to the buses now. please.
- 噢 不 - 我们得快点了 拜托
- Oh, no. - We need to hurry up, please.
来 睡一会儿吧
Come on, get some sleep.
等等！
Wait!
停停 拜托！
Hold it, please!
- 塔莎娜！ - 是帕特！
- Tatiana! - It's Pat!
- 塔莎娜！ - 阿彻夫人！
- Tatiana! - Madame Archer!
停车！停车 停车！
Stop the bus! Stop the bus, stop the bus!
来 来 来
Come. Come, come.
拜托 等等我们
Please, wait for us.
阿彻夫人 我很担心 还以为…
Madame Archer. I was so worried. I thought...
见到你真得太高兴了
It's wonderful to see you.
快来
Come quickly.
- 卡琳？ - 爱耐丝？
- Carine? - Anais?
爱耐丝？
Anais?
等着 只要一分钟
Just wait. It's gonna be just a minute now.
爱耐丝？卡琳？
Anais? Carine?
噢 上帝！
Oh, my God!
来 来 来！
Come, come, come!
嗨 卡琳 爱耐丝 嗨 你好吗 甜心？
Hello, Carine. Anais, hello. How are you, sweetheart?
来见见表姐妹？
Do you see your cousins?
他们说没位置了
They said there wasn't any room.
总会有的
There's always room.
保罗・卢斯赛伯吉纳保护了基加利米勒・科林斯饭店的
1268名图西族和胡图族难民
保罗和塔莎娜 还有他们的孩子罗杰、黛安、伊利、特丽莎
以及他们收养的侄女爱耐丝和卡琳现在住在比利时
塔莎娜的哥哥托马斯和他的妻子费登丝尚未被发现
2002年 奥古斯丁・比齐蒙戈将军在安哥拉被逮捕
并运往联合国坦桑尼亚的战争犯罪法庭
同一法庭上 部落民兵领袖乔治・卢塔甘达被判处终身监禁
种族屠杀于1994年7月结束 此时图西族叛乱分子
将胡图族军队及部族民兵驱赶到了刚果边境
他们留下了接近一百万具尸体
导演：特里・乔治
编剧：凯尔・皮尔森 特里・乔治
-=THE LAST FANTASY=-
荣誉出品
本字幕仅供学习交流 严禁用于商业途径
-=TLF字幕组=-
翻译：KOK
校对：KOK
片名：卢旺达饭店
主演：唐・奇德尔
主演：索菲・奥康尼多
主演：杰昆・菲尼克斯